<presentation>
	<title>Aesthetics: open space proximity</title>
	<runninghead>Values resulting from open space proximity</runninghead>
	<description>Aesthetic value module</description>
	<!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) -->
	<concept>aries:AestheticValueAnalysis</concept>  <!-- Ferd: does this needs to be updated (split) into viewsheds & proximity? -->
	
	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<name>Aesthetics: open space proximity</name>
		<title>Model coverage and general information</title>
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Aesthetic values are typically defined as the value derived from views 
			or proximity to open space.  These values often accrue to housing or property values 
			and are often measured using hedonic pricing.  Homeowners typically gain some combination 
			of benefits through sensory enjoyment of views of nearby open space, proximity to open 
			space for recreation, or privacy.  Spatial mapping of homeowners is relatively straightforward, 
			as housing units and open space have been frequently analyzed in hedonic studies of 
			amenity values.  The value of proximity has typically been found to decline with distance 
			from an accessible parcel of open space.</p>

			<p>The proximity source models account for the type of open space – either natural ecosystems 
			(e.g., forests, wetlands, beaches, riverfront, lakefront, grassland, desert) or 
			managed open space (e.g., cemeteries, farmland, golf courses) and its quality (e.g., area,
			protected status, water quality, potential for crime, fire threat).  Sink models simply account 
			for the location of highways that limit easy access, reduce privacy, and increase noise for nearby 
			residents.  Use models account for the location and value of housing and urban proximity, 
			which acts as a proxy for open space scarcity and congestion and has been shown to be a 
			key variable influencing the value of open space.</p>

		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/aesth.html" target="_blank">The aesthetic viewshed section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>
		
		<b>Additional contributors</b>: Dave Batker, Jim Pittman, Paula Swedeen.<br/> 
	    
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">U.S. National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		
	</page>
</presentation>