<!--
Copyright 2011 The ARIES Consortium (http://www.ariesonline.org)

This file is part of ARIES.

ARIES is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License,
or (at your option) any later version.

ARIES is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with ARIES.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<presentation>

  <title>Aesthetics: viewsheds</title>
  <runninghead>Values resulting from aesthetic viewsheds</runninghead>
  <description>The benefits of viewsheds</description>

  <!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) -->
  <concept>aries:AestheticViewshedAnalysis</concept>

  <!-- The storylines that this module can compute. One or more, and all their children scenarios are included. -->
  <model-storyline>aestheticService:AestheticViewsheds</model-storyline>

  <page>
    <id>info</id>
    <name>Aesthetics: viewsheds</name>
    <title>Model coverage and general information</title>
    <description><![CDATA[
    <p>Aesthetic values are typically defined as the value derived from views
    or proximity to open space.  These values often accrue to housing or property values
    and are often measured using hedonic pricing.  Park visitors (e.g., hikers) and
    drivers along scenic highways may also value scenic views, although we consider these
    values in ARIES using recreation models.  Spatial mapping of homeowners is relatively
    straightforward, as housing units and viewshed values have been frequently analyzed
    in hedonic studies of amenity values.  View values rely on an unimpeded line
    of sight to visually significant objects such as mountains or water bodies.</p>

    <p>Sources of aesthetically valuable views include mountains, water bodies, or specific
    vegetation types such as forests or riparian areas.  Users of aesthetic views are found
    in residential areas.  As a view travels from source to user, it may be physically blocked
    by buildings, trees, or topography.  Its quality may be depleted by air pollution or visual
    blight, such as highways, forest clearcuts, transmission lines, mines, or visually
    unappealing land use including commercial, industrial, or transportation.  Such sinks, or
    locations of visual blight, can also be mapped.  Higher concentrations of residential users
    or visual blight lead to higher levels of ecosystem service use or sinks, respectively.</p>
    ]]></description>
    <see-also><![CDATA[
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/modules/aesth.html" target="_blank">The aesthetic viewshed section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
    </p>
    ]]></see-also>
    <credits><![CDATA[
    <b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>

    <b>Additional contributors</b>: Dave Batker, Clark Bockelman, Jack
    Laskey, Jim Pittman, Ben Schubert, Paula Swedeen, Ben Zank.<br/>

    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">U.S. National Science Foundation</a>.
    ]]></credits>
  </page>

</presentation>
