<presentation>

	<title>Carbon sequestration and storage</title>
	<runninghead>The values accrued by any beneficiary of CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration and storage</runninghead>
	<description>The values accrued by any beneficiary of CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration and storage</description>
	<!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) -->
	<concept>carbonService:CarbonSourceValue</concept>
	
	<!-- all the models that apply and in which context -->
	<model>
		<id>core.models.carbon/identification-carbon</id>
		<context>core.contexts.beta/western_wa</context>
	</model>	

	<model>
		<id>core.models.carbon-ca/identification-carbon</id>
		<context>core.contexts.beta/ca_mark_watershed</context>
	</model>

	<model>
		<id>core.models.carbon-vt/identification-carbon</id>
		<context>core.contexts.beta/vt</context>
	</model>

	<model>	
		<id>core.models.carbon-san-pedro/identification-carbon</id>
		<context>core.contexts.beta/san_pedro_us</context>
	</model>	

	<model>
		<id>core.models.carbon-mg/identification-carbon</id>
		<context>core.contexts.beta/mg</context>
	</model>	
	
	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<!-- visible to user, for choices etc. -->
		<name>CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration and storage</name>
		<concept></concept>
		<title>General description</title>
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>This storyline computes estimates carbon sequestration by 
			terrestrial ecosystems - the net removal of carbon dioxide 
			(CO<sub>2</sub>) from the atmosphere and the avoidance of CO<sub>2</sub> emissions 
			from terrestrial ecosystems into the atmosphere via fire or 
			deforestation. CO<sub>2</sub> uptake from the atmosphere largely occurs 
			via photosynthesis. This carbon is stored as plant biomass 
			(in the trunks, branches, leaves and roots of the plants)
			and organic matter in the soil. Terrestrial carbon sequestration 
			depends on a series of factors including climatic conditions, 
			vegetation structure and successional stage, and land use 
			practices. </p>

			<p>In ARIES, we distinguish between ecosystem sources where
			carbon sequestration occurs. We also map sinks, or areas at risk 
			of releasing stored carbon, largely via fire or deforestation. 
			By subtracting the amount of stored carbon release from carbon 
			sequestration in a region of interest, we are left with the carbon 
			remaining available to offset anthropogenic emissions.  These greenhouse 
			gas emitters are the beneficiaries of carbon sequestration and storage. 
			Since greenhouse gas emitters benefit from the waste absorption 
			capacity of the biosphere, carbon sequestration and storage can 
			be divided among emitters. Existing and proposed systems to cap 
			and assign property rights to atmospheric greenhouse gas emissions 
			use this framework. In other words:</p>

			<quote><em>Carbon sequestration (source) – stored carbon release (sink) = carbon
			available to offset emissions (use)</em></quote>

			<p>By mapping levels of carbon sequestration, stored carbon release, and
			anthropogenic emissions in a common unit (tonnes C/ha.yr), we can fully
			describe regional carbon balances – the level of a region’s net
			release or uptake of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>. This will become increasingly
			important as local, state, and national governments continue to
			inventory greenhouse gas emissions and implement strategies to
			address climate change. Use of ecosystem carbon sequestration is rival and
			occurs at the global scale through atmospheric mixing.</p>  
		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
			<a href="http://www.ipcc.ch" target="_blank">IPCC web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, 
		Sergey Krivov, Brian Voigt.<br/>
		
		<b>Additional contributors</b>: Ted Auch, Mark Casias, Sam Gorton, Jennifer Wright, Dave Batker,
		Jim Pittman, Paula Swedeen. Miroslav Honzak.<br/> 
	    
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead></runninghead>
	</page>
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:VegetationAndSoilCarbonSequestration</concept>
		<title>Carbon Sequestration</title>
		<name>Atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> removed</name>
		<units>tonnes C/ha.year</units>
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>CO<sub>2</sub> sequestered. The amount of carbon taken up by vegetation and soils and added
			to biotic and soil carbon stocks. This is the quantity available for
			mitigating anthropogenic carbon emissions.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>This map is the most relevant output of the ARIES carbon model. 
				The value of the area in mitigating the adverse effects of rising 
				atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> is indicated by the amount of carbon sequestered
				by vegetation and soil.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>The data are in physical units of tonnes of carbon sequestered per hectare per
			year. As the output of the models is probabilistic, each point contains the probability 
			distribution of the amount of carbon. The distribution can be visualized by clicking
			on the map; the mean value and the coefficient of variation are reported along with
			the probabilities.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>This map has been computed at your request by a Bayesian model built and 
			   calibrated by the ARIES server when the area was selected.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
			<a href="http://www.ipcc.ch" target="_blank">IPCC web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>Tonnes of C sequestered by vegetation and soils</runninghead>
		<group>source</group>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>uncertainty-2d</plot-type>
		<!-- <statistics>totals</statistics> -->	
	</page>
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:StoredCarbonRelease</concept>
		<name> Stored carbon release</name>
		<title>Release of stored carbon</title>
		<group>sink</group>
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>The total emissions of carbon from the landscape, i.e., due to fire, deforestation, 
			   or other land use-land cover change, excluding emissions from fossil fuel combustion. </p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>This map is an output of the ARIES carbon model. The value of the 
				area in mitigating the adverse effects of climate change 
				is reduced when stored carbon in vegetation or soils is released.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>The data are in physical units of tonnes of carbon released per hectare per
			year. As the output of the models is probabilistic, each point contains the distribution
			probability of the amount of carbon released, based on the amount of stored carbon and 
			the probability of fire and/or deforestation. The distribution can be visualized by clicking
			on the map; the mean value and the coefficient of variation are reported along with
			the probabilities.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>This map has been computed at your request by a Bayesian model built and 
			   calibrated by the ARIES server when the area was selected.</p>
		]]></description>
		<runninghead>The total emissions of carbon from the landscape, i.e., due to fire, deforestation, or other land use-land cover change.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>uncertainty-2d</plot-type>
		<!-- <statistics>totals</statistics> -->	
		<units>tonnes C/ha.year</units>
	</page>
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:GreenhouseGasEmitters</concept>
		<name>Carbon emitted</name>
		<title>CO<sub>2</sub> emission from human activity</title>
		<group>use</group>
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>The beneficiaries of carbon sequestration and storage are greenhouse
			   gas emitters who release CO<sub>2</sub> into the atmosphere, relying on ecosystems 
			   to absorb and store carbon in order to avoid even larger rises in 
			   atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> than are currently seen.  Our carbon use models 
			   thus display greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>This map is used to identify the beneficiaries of CO<sub>2</sub> sequestration in 
			   this storyline.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>The data are in physical units of tonnes of carbon released each year due to fossil
			fuel combustion.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>  Spatially explicit data on greenhouse gas emissions exist for the United States.  
				Globally, we use population density data multiplied by per capita emissions
			    for the country or sub-national region of interest.</p>
		]]></description>
		<runninghead>Emitters benefit under a scenario of compensation</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
		<units>tonnes C/ha.year</units>
		<!-- <statistics>totals</statistics> -->	
	</page>
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:SoilCNRatio</concept>
		<title>Soil C:N ratio</title>
		<name>C/N ratio</name>
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>The ratio of carbon to nitrogen in soils influences the rate of sequestration
			of carbon from the vegetation, along with temperature ranges, land cover, vegetation
			types and evapotranspiration.  In some ecosystems, carbon sequestration and storage
			are predicted to be greater under higher soil C:N ratio values.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>Data are used as input to the sequestration (source) model.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are a unitless ratio of soil carbon:nitrogen concentrations.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>The data are derived from the FAO's global soil database.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>Ratio of carbon to nitrogen in soils</runninghead>
		<group>flow</group>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:SummerHighWinterLow</concept>
		<name>Seasonality</name>
		<title>Summer - Winter temperature range</title>
		<group />
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>The difference between mean summer high and winter low
				temperatures can be a meaningful predictor of net primary production.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>These data were derived from global mean temperature data and are used
				as an input in the ARIES carbon models for both carbon sequestration and 
				storage. Seasonality is predicted to affect carbon sequestration and storage,
				with greater sequestration and storage under lower seasonal temperature variability.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>The data are in physical units of degrees centigrade.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>This map has been reclassified from globally available data provided by
			   .</p>
		]]></description>
		<description>T</description>
		<runninghead>The difference between mean summer high and winter low
			temperatures.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:SuccessionalStage</concept>
		<title>Successional Stage</title>
		<name>Succession</name>
		<group />
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>The stage of vegetation regrowth following a disturbance event. 
			The rate of succession, type of late successional plant community, 
			and importance of succession in predicting ecosystem carbon sequestration
			and storage will vary widely in different ecosystems. Generally, we predict
			greater carbon storage in late successional ecosystems and greater
			sequestration in early to mid successional ecosystems.
			</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>BLM Interagency Vegetation Mapping Project for western Oregon and Washington.</p>
		]]></description>
				<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>The stage of vegetation growth influences CO<sub>2</sub> uptake.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:PercentVegetationCover</concept>
		<name>Tree canopy cover</name>
		<title>Percent tree canopy cover</title>
		<group />
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>Tree canopy data influences both carbon sequestration and 
			storage in most environments.  We generally predict greater carbon
			sequestration and storage in areas with greater tree canopy cover.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>The variable is used as input to compute carbon sequestration and 
			 storage distributions.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are the percentage of the ground surface covered by tree canopy.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>NLCD 2001 data in the United States; GLCF (University of Maryland) data used globally.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>Percent vegetative cover.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:HardwoodSoftwoodRatio</concept>
		<title>Hardwood:Softwood ratio</title>
		<name>Hardwood:Softwood</name>
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>Softwood and hardwood tree species grow at different rates, so they sequester and
			store atmospheric carbon in different ways. Generally, we assume softwoods will grow
			and sequester carbon at a greater rate early in their life, while hardwoods will grow
			more slowly (i.e., sequester less carbon annually) but will store more carbon in mature
			hardwood forests).</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>The ratio of hardwood to softwood enters the probabilistic model of carbon sequestration and/or storage.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>Reclassification of local forest type data.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.unep-wcmc.org" target="_blank">UNEP World Conservation Monitoring Centre</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead></runninghead>
		<group>flow</group>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
	<concept>carbonService:MeanAnnualPrecipitation</concept>
		<name>Precipitation</name>
		<title>Mean annual precipitation</title>
		<group />
		<description>
			<p>Ecosystems in regions with greater mean annual precipitation generally have greater carbon sequestration
			and/or storage.  Precipitation is particularly important in water-limited environments, where annual variation
			in precipitation strongly influences annual carbon sequestration.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>Annual precipitation enters the probabilistic model of carbon sequestration and/or storage, particularly in arid environments.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>The data are in physical units of millimeters of precipitation.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>Global or national-scale mean annual precipitation data.</p>
		</description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>No description given</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:FireFrequency</concept>
		<name>Fire</name>
		<title>Fire Frequency</title>
		<group />
		<description>
			<p>Fires are an important and in some cases predictable variable in
			determining release of carbon stored in biomass and soils.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>The likelihood of deforestation and fire, combined with the quantity of stored carbon in an
			ecosystem, can predict the amount of stored carbon that is released during deforestation or fire.
			Fire is a strong influence on carbon dynamics in fire-adapted systems or those that have been altered
			by fire supression or invasive species, and is a weaker influence in colder and wetter climates.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>State-level data on fire frequency and fire prone vegetation types.</p>
		</description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>No description given</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:Soilph</concept>
		<name>Soil pH</name>
		<title>Soil pH</title>
		<group />
		<description>
			h1. Role in models
			h1. Representation
			h1. Source
		</description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>No description given</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:PopulationDensity</concept>
		<name>Population</name>
		<title>Population density</title>
		<group />
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>Population density can influences carbon storage. In tropical nations with high 
			direct dependence on forests for firewood and other ecosystem goods, higher population density
			can lead to lower levels of forest carbon storage as woody debris and biomass are removed 
			for direct human use.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>This variable is used to help estimate the quantity of carbon stored in vegetation.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Gaston et al. (1998) define the discretization used here to model population density
			   effects on carbon levels. </p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>LANDSCAN global population density (Oak Ridge National Laboratory).</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			Gaston, G., S. Brown, M. Lorenzini, and K.D. Singh. 1998.  State and change in 
			carbon pools in the forests of tropical Africa.  Global Change Biology
			4: 97-114.<br/>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: LANDSCAN 30m coverages produced by Oak Ridge Natl.Labs.</br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<units>people/km2</units>
		<runninghead>No description given</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:DegradationStatus</concept>
		<title>Level of forest degradation</title>
		<name>Degradation</name>
		<group />
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Where forest degradation data are available, it can be used to train 
			probabilistic models so that its effect is taken into consideration in 
			predicting carbon sequestration and storage.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>Forest degradation data are available for Madagascar, a nation with high deforestation rates
			and levels of forest degradation.  In degraded forests, we expect lower levels of carbon sequestration
			and storage.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical, and identify degraded forest and savanna ecosystems.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>Foiben-Taosarintanini Madagasikara (FTM), Madagsacar national land cover.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>Degradation of forests can influence sequestration.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:Slope</concept>
		<name>Slope</name>
		<title>Slope class</title>
		<group />
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Soil on slopes can be more easily washed away, particularly in the absence of protective
			vegetation.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>Areas on steep slopes are predicted to have lower levels of soil carbon storage,
			all else being equal.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>The data are in physical units of degrees slope.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>Data are derived from a global 90 m SRTM digital elevation map.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>Slope determines likelihood of soil washed away.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
	<concept>carbonService:FireThreatClass</concept>
		<name>Fire Risk</name>
		<title>Class of fire threat</title>
		<group />
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Fires are an important and in some cases predictable variable in
			determining release of carbon stored in biomass and soils.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>The likelihood of deforestation and fire, combined with the quantity of stored carbon in an
			ecosystem, can predict the amount of stored carbon that is released during deforestation or fire.
			Fire is a strong influence on carbon dynamics in fire-adapted systems or those that have been altered
			by fire supression or invasive species, and is a weaker influence in colder and wetter climates.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>State-level data on fire frequency and fire prone vegetation types.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>No description given</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:VegetationType</concept>
		<name>Vegetation</name>
		<title>Vegetation type</title>
		<group />
		<description language="html"><![CDATA[
			<p>Different plant community or land cover types have different carbon 
			sequestration rates and different capacity to store carbon.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>Data are used in some models to estimate differential carbon sequestration and/or
			storage in ecosystems such as forests, grasslands, and urban areas.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>NLCD or other land use/land cover data.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>Vegetation type is a factor in defining sequestration and storage capacities.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:SoilOxygenConditions</concept>
		<name>Soil oxygen</name>
		<title>Soil oxygen conditions</title>
		<group />
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>The presence of oxygen (aerobic environments) in soils allows respiration to take place, 
			with CO<sub>2</sub> being released. In anaerobic environments such as wetlands, minimal soil
			respiration occurs, and greater buildup of soil carbon can occur (though generation of methane,
			a powerful greenhouse gas) often also occurs.  Wetland degradation, such as through declining
			water tables, can also allow oxidation of soil carbon, reducing their carbon storage.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>Greater soil carbon storage is expected in wetland than upland environments, all else being equal.
			We currently do not consider the role of methane production by wetlands in the ARIES carbon models.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are represented as the presence/absence of wetlands.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>Land cover data, such as the U.S. NLCD, global GLC2000, or European CORINE datasets
			 are used to identify the presence of wetlands.</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>The presence of oxygen allows CO<sub>2</sub>-producing respiration to take place.</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>
	
	<page>
		<concept>carbonService:DeforestationRiskClass</concept>
		<name>Deforestation</name>
		<title>Risk of deforestation</title>
		<group />
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Areas at greater risk of deforestation is are likely to lead to greater stored carbon release.</p>
			<h1>Role in models</h1>
			<p>The likelihood of deforestation and fire, combined with the quantity of stored carbon in an
			ecosystem, can predict the amount of stored carbon that is released during deforestation or fire.
			Deforestation acts as a particularly strong influence in the model in tropical nations with higher
			deforestation rates and weaker land tenure and enforcement of legal limits on forest clearing.</p>
			<h1>Representation</h1>
			<p>Data are categorical.</p>
			<h1>Source</h1>
			<p>GLCF (University of Maryland).</p>
		]]></description>
		<see-also language="html"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits language="html"><![CDATA[
	    <b>Data provided by</b>: </br>
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
		<runninghead>No description given</runninghead>
		<plot-type default="true">geosurface-2d</plot-type>
		<plot-type>geocontour-2d</plot-type>
	</page>

	
</presentation>