<presentation>

	<title>Carbon sequestration and storage</title>
	<runninghead>Climate mitigation from capture and storage of atmospheric carbon</runninghead>
	<description>The benefits to humans of sequestering and storing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub></description>
	<!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) 
		 FIXME: change to an ESClass concept for the given ES. -->
	<concept>aries:CarbonAnalysis</concept>
	
	<!-- the storylines that this module can compute. One or more, and all their children scenarios are included. -->
	<model-storyline>carbonService:CarbonSourceValue</model-storyline>

	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<name>Carbon sequestration and storage</name>
		<title>Model coverage and general information</title>
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Ecosystems contribute to reduced atmospheric carbon dioxide 
			(CO<sub>2</sub>) through carbon sequestration - the removal of CO<sub>2</sub> from 
			the atmosphere and avoided release of stored carbon from terrestrial
			ecosystems into the atmosphere.  CO<sub>2</sub> uptake from the atmosphere 
			largely occurs via photosynthesis. This carbon is stored as plant
			biomass (in the trunks, branches, leaves and roots of the plants)
			and organic matter in the soil (IPCC 2000). Terrestrial carbon
			sequestration depends on a series of factors including climatic
			conditions, vegetation structure and successional stage, and
			land use practices.</p>

			<p>In ARIES, we distinguish between ecosystem sources where
			carbon sequestration occurs. We also map sinks, or areas at risk 
			of releasing stored carbon, largely via fire or deforestation. 
			By subtracting the amount of stored carbon release from carbon 
			sequestration in a region of interest, we are left with the carbon 
			remaining available to offset anthropogenic emissions.  These greenhouse 
			gas emitters are the beneficiaries of carbon sequestration and storage. 
			Since greenhouse gas emitters benefit from the waste absorption 
			capacity of the biosphere, carbon sequestration and storage can 
			be divided among emitters. Existing and proposed systems to cap 
			and assign property rights to atmospheric greenhouse gas emissions 
			use this framework. In other words:</p>

			<quote><em>Carbon sequestration (source) – stored carbon release (sink) = carbon
			available to offset emissions (use)</em></quote>

			<p>By mapping levels of carbon sequestration, stored carbon release, and
			anthropogenic emissions in a common unit (tonnes C/ha.yr), we can fully
			describe regional carbon balances – the level of a region’s net
			release or uptake of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub>. This will become increasingly
			important as local, state, and national governments continue to
			inventory greenhouse gas emissions and implement strategies to
			address climate change. Use of ecosystem carbon sequestration is rival and
			occurs at the global scale through atmospheric mixing.</p>  
		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon sequestration and storage section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, 
		Sergey Krivov, Brian Voigt.<br/>
		
		<b>Additional contributors</b>: Ted Auch, Mark Casias, Sam Gorton, Jennifer Wright, Dave Batker,
		Jim Pittman, Paula Swedeen, Miroslav Honzak.<br/> 
	    
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
	</page>

</presentation>