<presentation>

	<title>Climate mitigation</title>
	<runninghead>Climate mitigation from capture of atmospheric carbon</runninghead>
	<description>The benefits to humans of sequestering and storing atmospheric CO2</description>
	<!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) 
		 FIXME: change to an ESClass concept for the given ES. -->
	<concept>aries:CarbonAnalysis</concept>
	
	<!-- the storylines that this module can compute. One or more, and all their children scenarios are included. -->
	<model-storyline>carbonService:CarbonSourceValue</model-storyline>

	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<name>Climate Mitigation</name>
		<title>Model coverage and general information</title>
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Carbon sequestration by terrestrial ecosystems is the net
			removal of carbon dioxide (CO2) from the atmosphere or the
			avoidance of CO2 emissions from terrestrial
			ecosystems into the atmosphere. The removal process includes
			CO2 uptake from the atmosphere by all chlorophyllous plants,
			through photosynthesis. This carbon (C) is stored as plant
			biomass (in the trunks, branches, leaves and roots of the plants)
			and organic matter in the soil (IPCC 2000). Terrestrial carbon
			sequestration depends on a series of factors including climatic
			conditions, vegetation structure and successional stage, and
			land use practices.</p>

			<p>In ARIES, we distinguish between ecosystem sources of
			carbon sequestration capacity capable of removing CO2 from the
			atmosphere and storing carbon in vegetation and soils. We also map
			sinks, or areas that release stored carbon, largely via fire or
			deforestation. By subtracting the amount of stored carbon release
			from carbon sequestration in a region of interest, we are left with
			the carbon remaining available to offset anthropogenic emissions.
			Greenhouse gas emitters can be conceptualized as the beneficiaries of
			carbon sequestration and storage. Since greenhouse gas emitters
			benefit from the waste absorption capacity of the biosphere, carbon
			sequestration and storage can be divided among emitters. Existing and
			proposed systems to cap and assign property rights to atmospheric
			greenhouse gas emissions use this framework. In other words:</p>

			<quote><em>Carbon sequestration (source) – stored carbon release (sink) = carbon
			available to offset emissions (use)</em></quote>

			<p>By mapping levels of carbon sequestration, stored carbon release, and
			anthropogenic emissions in a common unit (tonnes C/ha.yr), we can fully
			describe regional carbon balances – the level of a region’s net
			release or uptake of atmospheric CO2. This will become increasingly
			important as local, state, and national governments continue to
			inventory greenhouse gas emissions and implement strategies to
			address climate change. Use of carbon sequestration is rival and
			occurs at the global scale through atmospheric mixing.</p>  
		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/carbon.html" target="_blank">The carbon section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, 
		Sergey Krivov, Brian Voigt.<br/>
		
		<b>Additional contributors</b>: Ted Auch, Mark Casias, Sam Gorton, Jennifer Wright, Dave Batker,
		Jim Pittman, Paula Swedeen. Miroslav Honzak.<br/> 
	    
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
	</page>

</presentation>