<!--
Copyright 2011 The ARIES Consortium (http://www.ariesonline.org)

This file is part of ARIES.

ARIES is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License,
or (at your option) any later version.

ARIES is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with ARIES.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<presentation>

  <title>Recreation</title>
  <runninghead>Values resulting from ecosystem contributions toward recreational activities</runninghead>
  <description>The case study</description>

  <!-- The concept of the main observation (the top-level model). -->
  <concept>aries:RecreationAnalysis</concept>

  <!-- The storylines that this module can compute. One or more, and all their children scenarios are included. -->
  <model-storyline>recreationService:MountainViewUse</model-storyline>
  <model-storyline>recreationService:BirdingUse</model-storyline>
  <model-storyline>recreationService:HuntingUse</model-storyline>
  <model-storyline>recreationService:WildlifeViewingUse</model-storyline>

  <page>
    <id>info</id>
    <name>Recreation</name>
    <title>Model coverage and general information</title>
    <description><![CDATA[
    <p>Ecosystems provide settings for a diverse array of recreational
    activities. Recreational values are among the most well-recognized of
    all ecosystem services by the public, and human preferences for
    recreation have been well-studied by economists and other social
    scientists. From a spatial perspective, we can map sources of
    recreational value (areas capable of providing the natural setting
    needed for a particular activity), sinks of recreational value
    (landscape features that reduce those source values, if applicable),
    and the users of a particular recreation area for a given activity.
    Users may simultaneously value a particular bundle of recreational
    attributes (e.g., the quality of an area for hunting or fishing plus
    the quality of scenic views), infrastructure that contributes to the
    recreational experience (i.e., trails, other facilities), congestion
    or lack thereof (with potential resulting visitor response), and the
    management policies that facilitate a particular recreational
    experience. The ARIES recreation models are intended to solely map an
    ecosystem’s capacity to support a particular recreational activity, as
    opposed to the other attributes that contribute to the overall quality
    of a recreational experience, with the understanding that only the
    ecosystem attributes supporting recreation are a true ecosystem
    service. By mapping the ecosystem’s contribution toward different
    recreational attributes, we can explore tradeoffs between different
    types of recreational use, tradeoffs between recreation and other
    ecosystem services, and relative preferences for certain recreational
    attributes.</p>

    <p>In our current case studies, we map scenic viewsheds as they
    are valued by hikers to mountain summits, usinga viewshed model
    described in the aesthetic models. We also model wildlife-based
    recreational values for birding, hunting, and wildlife viewing.
    Although we do not yet incorporate flow models for transportation,
    these will be implemented in the future as described below.</p>

    <p>A recreation flow model accounts for travel from a person’s
    home to a particular location suitable for that recreational activity.
    Travel cost and recreational site choice studies also use basic
    transportation routing to connect recreationists to recreation sites,
    but typically do not map the process or facilitate comparisons with
    other ecosystem services. In this way, a recreation flow model can
    show from where a particular recreation area draws its users or to
    which (substitute) areas a specific recreational user group in a
    region gravitates toward. All recreation models thus contain a
    transportation network-based flow model to move people toward
    recreational areas capable of supporting their activities of interest.
    While flows of most other ecosystem services are defined biophysically
    (i.e., through movement of water, nutrients, sediment, or atmospheric
    gases), biologically (i.e., through migration and movement of key
    species), or through trade networks (i.e., for ecosystem goods),
    recreational flows are based on human preferences for a particular
    activity and perceptions about places capable of providing a desirable
    setting for that activity. This adds a great deal of complexity to
    understanding recreational flows, as preferences can be shaped by past
    experiences and place attachment, as well as distance and subjective
    measures of a site’s suitability for a given recreational
    activity.</p>
    
    <p>To calculate the recreation source value to feed into the
    transportation flow model, an optional initial physical or biological
    flow model may also be needed (e.g., to identify spatial dependencies
    for areas having high quality viewsheds, providing sources of water
    for water-based recreation, or providing habitat for recreationally
    valued species). For instance, a physical or biological flow model
    could show where high-quality views are provided to key vantage points
    (along with visual blight that reduces view quality), where runoff is
    provided to a watershed valued for rafting or fishing, or where
    critical habitat outside a protected area supports populations of
    recreationally valuable species. These models can then show off-site
    areas outside of the directly valued recreational resource that are
    critical toward maintaining the quality of that resource. The
    transportation flow model is then used to link source (recreational
    use) points to the location of recreational users. For viewsheds, we
    use a viewshed model to identify mountain summits that can provide
    scenic views, with view quality estimated using a line of sight flow
    model. We then apply a transportation flow model to link potential
    users to these scenic trails themselves.</p>

    <p>Given the heterogeneity of recreational preferences in
    different parts of the world, we do not currently envision creating a
    generalized global ARIES recreation model, but instead plan to develop
    local case studies such as those described in this chapter, along with
    other recreational activities, as we develop new case studies. These
    future case studies could allow us to expand the geographic coverage
    of ARIES recreation models while enabling us to better understand when
    and where development of national or global scale recreation models
    might be more appropriate.</p>
    ]]></description>
    <see-also><![CDATA[
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/modules/rec.html"
    target="_blank">Recreation model details from the ARIES website</a><br/>
    </p>
    ]]></see-also>
    <credits><![CDATA[
    <b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>

    <b>Additional contributors</b>: Rose Graves.<br/>

    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">U.S. National Science Foundation</a>.
    ]]></credits>
  </page>

</presentation>
