<presentation>
	<title>Case study</title>
	<runninghead>ARIES case study</runninghead>
	<description>An ARIES case study start with context selection, shown in the window.</description>

	<!-- main storyline namespace for the ARIES agent that runs them -->
	<id>aries</id>
	
	<!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) -->
	<concept>aries:CaseStudy</concept>
	
	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<name>Case Study</name>
		<title>Region of interest</title>
		<description title="Navigating an ARIES case study"><![CDATA[
		<p>With growing interest in using ecosystem services for decision making, 
		demand has grown for systematic methods and tools to quantify ecosystem 
		service values. ARIES maps the potential provision of ecosystem services 
		(<b>sources</b>), their users (<b>use</b>), and biophysical features that can deplete
		 service flows (<b>sinks</b>) using ecological process models or Bayesian models.
		 ARIES then uses a series of agent-based flow algorithms to map actual 
		 <b>service flow</b> from ecosystems to people.</p>
		 <h1>How to use the ARIES explorer</h1>
		 <p>ARIES models are presented as <b>storylines</b> that are computed on demand. You are looking at the main 
		 case study descriptor for the area you chose. The navigator below lists the modules that
		 have storylines available to compute in this area (with a colored globe) and those that do not
		 (with a grey globe). You can click on the modules to show their individual description and
		 see the list of the storylines they contain.</p>
		 <p>Each storyline is computed individually and tells a story about a specific aspect
		 of a given ecosystem service in this area. The explorer for storylines is structured as
		 a presentation that explains in detail the role, meaning and provenance of each 
		 input and output map.</p>
		 ]]></description>
		<runninghead></runninghead>
		<see-also title="External links"><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<br/>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org" target="_blank">The ARIES web site</a><br/>
			<a href="mailto:info@ariesonline.org" target="_blank">Submit an inquiry</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Technical team</b>: Ferdinando Villa, Ken Bagstad, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>
	    <b>Main project funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.<br/>
	    <b>Marine models funding</b>: <a href="http://www.unep-wcmc-org" target="_blank">UNEP World Conservation Monitoring Centre</a>.
		]]></credits>
	</page>
	
</presentation>