<presentation>
	<title>Fish values</title>
	<runninghead>Fisheries</runninghead>
	<description>Values of fish resources</description>
	<!-- the concept of the main observation (the top-level model) -->
	<concept>aries:FisheriesAnalysis</concept>

	<model-storyline>fisheries:SubsistenceFishProvision</model-storyline>

	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<name>Fisheries</name>
		<title>Model coverage and general information</title>
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>Subsistence harvesting of ecosystem goods – food, fuel,
			fiber, and other basic resources – is a critical contributor to
			livelihoods in much of the developing world as well as in parts of
			developed nations (MA 2005). These ecosystem goods have been termed
			the “GDP of the poor” (TEEB 2008), since they provide employment and
			livelihoods for so many of the world’s poor while not being monetized
			as part of traditional national economic accounts like GDP. Such
			societal dependence on subsistence fisheries, combined with the
			recognition that the world’s oceans are in a crisis due to
			overfishing, pollution, and climate change (Diaz and Rosenberg 2008,
			Cooley and Doney 2009, Worm et al. 2009, Hoegh-Guldberg and Bruno
			2010) strongly argues the case for more sustainable management of
			marine / aquatic resources. By mapping societal dependence on
			ecosystem services, we can better demonstrate the linkages between
			ecosystems and human well-being for subsistence fisheries. In
			addition, by linking flows of sediment, nutrients, and fresh water
			from land into the coastal zone, the complex tradeoffs between land
			management choices and provision of coastal and marine ecosystem
			services can be illuminated. This understanding is critical given the
			growing recognition of complex spatial flows of ecosystem processes
			and services between terrestrial, coastal, and marine environments
			(McCulloch et al. 2003, Fabricus 2005, Silvestri and Kershaw 2010).</p>

			<p>We developed our initial subsistence fisheries case study in
			Madagascar due to its high rate of poverty, dependence on fisheries
			as a key protein source in rural communities, and prevalent
			deforestation-driven sedimentation and erosion processes, which
			strongly affect its coastal and marine systems (see the ARIES
			Modelling guide for a discussion of ARIES sedimentation models for
			Madagascar). The Madagascar models rely on global spatial datasets
			for fisheries, population density, and poverty, combined with
			non-spatial data on national fisheries use from the FAO (2008) and
			The Sea Around Us Project (2010). Since such data are available for
			all nations, it is quite feasible to extend coverage of this
			subsistence fisheries model to other countries. However, since key
			harvested fish species and dependence on subsistence fisheries differ
			by nation, models should be specialized on a nation-by-nation basis,
			rather than as part of a generalized global model, as is the case for
			some other ecosystem services.</p>

		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/fisheries.html" target="_blank">The fisheries section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt, Ferdinando Villa.<br/>
		
		<b>Additional contributors</b>: William Cheung, Silvia Silvestri, Kristian Teleki, Monica Barcellos-Harris, Nicola Barnard, Liz Selig, Carmen Lacambra, Louisa Woods.<br/> 
	    
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.unep-wcmc.org" target="_blank">UNEP World Conservation Monitoring Centre</a>.
		]]></credits>
	</page>

</presentation>