<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!--
Copyright 2011 The ARIES Consortium (http://www.ariesonline.org)

This file is part of ARIES.

ARIES is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License,
or (at your option) any later version.

ARIES is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with ARIES.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<rdf:RDF
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#"
  xmlns:time="http://www.integratedmodelling.org/time#"
  xmlns:ima="http://www.integratedmodelling.org/ima#"
  xmlns:documentation="http://www.integratedmodelling.org/documentation#">
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-2">
  <rdfs:label>
    Costanza et al., Nature, 1997.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The value of the world's ecosystem services and
      natural capital.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Costanza, R., d'Arge, R., de Groot, R., Farber,
      S., Grasso, M., Hannon,B., Limburg,K., Naeem,S., O'Neill,R.V., Paruelo,J.,
      Raskiin,R.G., Sutton,P., Van den Belt, M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The value of the world's ecosystem services and
      natural capital.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1997
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      253-260
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The services of ecological systems and the natural
      capital stocks that produce them are critical to the functioning of the
      Earth's life-support system. They contribute to human welfare, both
      directly and indirectly, and therefore represent part of the total
      economic value of the planet. We have estimated the current economic value
      of 17 ecosystem services for 16 biomes, based on published studies and a
      few original calculations. For the entire biosphere, the value (most of
      which is outside the market) is estimated to be in the range of US$16-54
      trillion (10(12)) per year, with an average of US$33 trillion per year.
      Because of the nature of the uncertainties, this must be considered a
      minimum estimate. Global gross national product total is around US$18
      trillion per year.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    year trillion around total product national gross Global estimate minimum considered must this uncertainties nature Because average with range estimated outside which value biosphere entire calculations original studies published based services ecosystem economic current have planet part represent therefore indirectly directly both welfare human contribute They system Earth's functioning critical them produce that stocks capital natural systems ecological world's Belt Sutton Limburg Hannon Grasso Farber Groot Costanza Nature
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-3">
  <rdfs:label>
    Kim, Global biogeochemical cycles, 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The Global Carbon Cycle
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Holmen Kim
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The Global Carbon Cycle
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Global biogeochemical
	cycles.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      239--262
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Cycle Carbon Global Holmen cycles biogeochemical The Kim
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-4">
  <rdfs:label>
    Broecker et al., Journal of Geophysical Research,
      1966.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Calcium carbonate precipitation on the Bahama
      Banks
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Broecker,W.S.,
      Takahashi,T.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Calcium carbonate precipitation on the Bahama
      Banks
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1966
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Geophysical
	Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      71
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1575-1602
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Banks Bahama precipitation carbonate Calcium Takahashi Research Geophysical Journal the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-13">
  <rdfs:label>
    Brookshire et al., American Economic Review, 1982.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Valuing public goods: a comparision of survey and
      hedonic approach
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Brookshire,D., Thayer,M.A., Schulze,W.D.,
      D'Arge,R.C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Valuing public goods: a comparision of survey and
      hedonic approach
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1982
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      American Economic
	Review
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      72
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      165-177
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    approach hedonic survey goods public Valuing Schulze Thayer Brookshire Review Economic American and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-14">
  <rdfs:label>
    Burke et al., Ecological Applications, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Soil organic matter recovery in semiarid
      grasslands: implications for the conservation reserve
      program.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Burke,I.C., Lauenroth,W.K.,
      Coffin,D.P.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Soil organic matter recovery in semiarid grasslands:
      implications for the conservation reserve program.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
	Applications
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      5
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      793-801
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Although the effects of cultivation on soil
      organic matter and nutrient supply capacity are well understood,
      relatively little work has been done on the long-term recovery of soils
      from cultivation. We sampled soils from 12 locations within the Pawnee
      National Grasslands of northeastern Colorado, each having native fields
      and fields that were historically cultivated but abandoned 50 yr ago. We
      also sampled fields that had been cultivated for at least 50 yr at 5 of
      these locations. Our results demonstrated that soil organic matter, silt
      content, microbial biomass, potentially mineralizable N, and potentially
      respirable C were significantly lower on cultivated fields than on native
      fields. Both cultivated and abandoned fields also had significantly lower
      soil organic matter and silt contents than native fields. Abandoned
      fields, however, were not significantly different from native fields with
      respect to microbial biomass, potentially mineralizable N, or respirable
      C. In addition, we found that the characteristic small-scale heterogeneity
      of the shortgrass steppe associated with individuals of the dominant
      plant, Bouteloua gracilis, had recovered on abandoned fields. Soil beneath
      plant canopies had an average of 200 g/m(2) more C than between-plant
      locations. We suggest that 50 yr is an adequate time for recovery of
      active soil organic matter and nutrient availability, but recovery of
      total soil organic matter pools is a much slower process. Plant population
      dynamics may play an important role in the recovery of shortgrass steppe
      ecosystems from disturbance, such that establishment of perennial grasses
      determines the rate of organic matter recovery.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    recovery matter organic rate determines grasses perennial establishment that such disturbance from ecosystems steppe role important play dynamics population Plant process slower pools soil total availability nutrient active time adequate suggest locations than more average canopies plant beneath Soil fields abandoned recovered dominant individuals with associated heterogeneity characteristic found addition respirable mineralizable potentially biomass microbial respect native different significantly were however Abandoned contents silt lower also cultivated Both content demonstrated results these least been sampled historically having each Colorado northeastern Grasslands National Pawnee within soils cultivation term long done work little relatively understood well capacity supply effects Although program reserve conservation implications grasslands semiarid Coffin Lauenroth Burke Applications Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-15">
  <rdfs:label>
    Bergstrom et al., Ecological Economics, 1990.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic value of wetlands-based
      recreation
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Bergstrom,J.C., Soll, J.R., Titre,J.P.,
      Wright,V.L.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic value of wetlands-based
      recreation
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
	Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      2
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      129-147
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    recreation value Economic Wright Titre Soll Bergstrom Economics Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-16">
  <rdfs:label>
    Bockstael et al., Ecological Economics, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Ecological economic modeling and valuation of
    ecosystems
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Bockstael,N., Costanza,R., Strand,I., Boynton,W.
    Bell,K.,Kainger,L.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Ecological economic modeling and valuation of
    ecosystems
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      14
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      143-159
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    We are attempting to integrate ecological and
    economic modeling and analysis in order to improve our understanding of
    regional systems, assess potential future impacts of various land-use,
    development, and agricultural policy options, and to better assess the
    value of ecological systems. Starting with an existing spatially
    articulated ecosystem model of the Patuxent River drainage basin in
    Maryland, we are adding modules to endogenize the agricultural components
    of the system (especially the impacts of agricultural practices and crop
    choice) and the process of land-use decision making. The integrated model
    will allow us to evaluate the indirect effects over long time horizons of
    current policy options. These effects are almost always ignored in partial
    analyses, although they may be very significant and may reverse many
    long-held assumptions and policy predictions. This paper is a progress
    report on this modeling effort, indicating our motivations, ideas, and
    plans for completion.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    completion plans ideas motivations indicating effort modeling this report progress paper This predictions policy assumptions many reverse significant very they although analyses partial ignored always almost effects These options current horizons time long over indirect evaluate allow will model integrated making decision land process crop practices agricultural impacts system components modules adding Maryland basin drainage River Patuxent ecosystem articulated spatially existing with Starting systems ecological value assess better development various future potential regional understanding improve order analysis economic integrate attempting ecosystems valuation Ecological Boynton Strand Costanza Economics
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-17">
  <rdfs:label>
    Burke et al., Soil Science. Society of Amerian Journal,
    1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Texture, climate, and cultivaiton effects on soil
    organic content in US grassland soils.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Burke,I.C., Yonker,C.M., Parton,W.J., Cole,C.V.,
    Flach,K., Schimel, D.S.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Texture, climate, and cultivaiton effects on soil
    organic content in US grassland soils.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Science. Society of Amerian
      Journal
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      53
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      800-805
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils grassland content organic soil effects climate Texture Schimel Flach Cole Parton Yonker Burke Journal Society Science Soil
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-18">
  <rdfs:label>
    Chopra, Economic Botany, 1993.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The value of non-timber forest products: an
    estimation for tropical deciduous forests in
    India.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Chopra,K.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The value of non-timber forest products: an
    estimation for tropical deciduous forests in India.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1993
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Economic Botany
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      47
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      251-257
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Alteration of forested land to other uses incurs
    costs to a nation's economy that are frequently not calculated in
    estimates of national productivity. Alternative methods of value are
    discussed and employed to evaluate the non-timber products of India's
    tropical deciduous forests. Many undervalued resources found in these
    forests are described, and monetary value ascribed to them, to demonstrate
    the importance of the resources to the Indian economy.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    economy Indian resources importance demonstrate them ascribed value monetary described forests these found undervalued Many deciduous tropical India's products evaluate employed discussed methods Alternative productivity national estimates calculated frequently that nation's costs incurs uses other land forested Alteration India estimation forest Chopra Botany Economic
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-19">
  <rdfs:label>
    Costanza et al., Man, Environment, Space and Time,
    1985.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Theories and methods of valuation ofnatural
    systems: a comparison of willingness-to-pay and energy analysis based
    approaches.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Costanza, R.,
    Farber,S.C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Theories and methods of valuation ofnatural systems:
    a comparison of willingness-to-pay and energy analysis based
    approaches.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1985
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Man, Environment, Space and
      Time
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      4
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1-38
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    approaches based analysis energy comparison systems valuation methods Theories Farber Costanza Time Space Environment
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-20">
  <rdfs:label>
    Copeland et al., Journal of Geophysical Research,
    1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Potential climatic impacts of vegetation change: a
    regional modelling study.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Copeland,J.H., Pielke,R.A.,
    Kittel,T.G.F.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Potential climatic impacts of vegetation change: a
    regional modelling study.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Geophysical
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      101
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      7409
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The human species has been modifying the landscape
    long before the development of modern agrarian techniques. Much of the
    land area of the conterminous United States is currently used for
    agricultural production. In certain regions this change in vegetative
    cover from its natural state may have led to local climatic change. A
    regional climate version of the Colorado State University Regional
    Atmospheric Modeling System was used to assess the impact of a natural
    versus current vegetation distribution on the weather and climate of July
    1989. The results indicate that coherent regions of substantial changes,
    of both positive and negative sign, in screen height temperature,
    humidity, wind speed, and precipitation are a possible consequence of land
    use change throughout the United States. The simulated changes in the
    screen height quantities were closely related to changes in the vegetation
    parameters of albedo, roughness length, leaf area index, and fractional
    coverage.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    coverage fractional index area leaf length roughness albedo parameters vegetation changes related closely were quantities height screen simulated States United throughout change land consequence possible precipitation speed wind humidity temperature sign negative positive both substantial regions coherent that indicate results July climate weather distribution current versus natural impact assess used System Modeling Atmospheric Regional University State Colorado version regional climatic local have state from cover vegetative this certain production agricultural currently conterminous Much techniques agrarian modern development before long landscape modifying been species human study modelling impacts Potential Kittel Copeland Research Geophysical Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-21">
  <rdfs:label>
    Crawford et al., Ecology, 1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Predation by birds on spruce budworm, Choristoneura
    fumiferana: functional, nemerical and total
    responses.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Crawford, H.S.,
    Jennings,D.T.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Predation by birds on spruce budworm, Choristoneura
    fumiferana: functional, nemerical and total
    responses.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      70
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      152-163
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    responses total functional spruce birds Predation Jennings Crawford Ecology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-22">
  <rdfs:label>
    Cruz et al., Journal of Philippine Development, 1988.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The on-site and downstream costs of soil erosion in
    the Magat and Pantabangan watersheds.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Cruz,W., Francisco,H.A., Conway,
    Z.T.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The on-site and downstream costs of soil erosion in
    the Magat and Pantabangan watersheds.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1988
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Philippine
      Development
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      26
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      85-
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    watersheds Magat erosion soil costs downstream Conway Francisco Cruz Development Philippine Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-23">
  <rdfs:label>
    Dixon et al., Tropical Coastal Area Management, 1988.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic evaluaiton of Coastal Resources: the El
    Nino Study.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Dixon,J.A.,
    Hodgson,G.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic evaluaiton of Coastal Resources: the El Nino
    Study.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1988
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Tropical Coastal Area
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      5-7
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Study Nino Resources Coastal Economic Hodgson Dixon Management Area Tropical
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-24">
  <rdfs:label>
    Echeverria et al., Ecological Economics, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Valuation of non-priced amenities provided by the
    biological resources whithin the Monteverde Cloud Forest preserve, Costa
    Rita.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Echeverria,J., Hanrahan,M.,
    Solorzano,R.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Valuation of non-priced amenities provided by the
    biological resources whithin the Monteverde Cloud Forest preserve, Costa
    Rita.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      13
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      43-52
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    To quantify the economic benefits of the Monteverde
    Cloud Forest Preserve and to test the contingent valuation method in a
    third world setting, a contingent valuation survey was designed with five
    experimental treatments. These determined an overall expected value per
    visitor; determined and compared two ways of eliciting value, single
    versus annual lump-sum payments; and compared average values of Costa
    Rican versus non-Costa Rican visitors. Visitors were willing to pay to
    prevent the Preserve's conversion to agricultural uses. Monteverde's value
    as a cloud forest preserve appears much higher than any value it might
    have in agricultural use. Despite lower incomes, Costa Rican visitors
    valued the Preserve more highly than non-Costa Rican visitors. Visitors
    may have differentiated only weakly between greatly differing bid amounts.
    Expected values derived from econometric analysis of the differing
    experimental treatments suggest that further methodological adaptation of
    the contingent valuation method may be required (1) when it is applied in
    third world settings, and (2) when precision is critical in estimating
    WTPs.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    estimating critical precision when settings world third applied required method valuation contingent adaptation methodological further that suggest treatments experimental differing analysis econometric from derived values Expected amounts greatly between weakly only differentiated have Visitors visitors Rican than highly more Preserve valued Costa incomes lower Despite agricultural might value higher much appears preserve forest cloud uses conversion prevent willing were versus average compared payments annual single eliciting ways determined visitor expected overall These five with designed survey setting test Forest Cloud Monteverde benefits economic quantify Rita resources biological provided amenities Valuation Solorzano Hanrahan Echeverria Economics Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-25">
  <rdfs:label>
    Edwards, Coastal Management, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The demand for Galapagos vacations: estimation and
    application to wildness preservation.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Edwards, S.F.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The demand for Galapagos vacations: estimation and
    application to wildness preservation.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Coastal
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      19
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      155-199
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The demand for Galapagos vacations by ecotourists
    was estimated using hedonic demand analysis, a technique being developed
    by environmental economists. In turn, the demand model was used to explore
    how a fiscal policy of maximizing tax revenues could help to satisfy the
    alleged incompatible goals of wilderness preservation and economic growth.
    Constrained to a carrying capacity of 125,000 visitor days, there is
    potential to raise about $30 million (U.S.) by substantially increasing
    the entrance fee charged to ecotourists. This tax revenue could be used to
    finance both conservation of the Galapagos wilderness and investment in
    Ecuador's economy.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    economy investment wilderness Galapagos conservation both finance used could revenue This charged entrance increasing substantially million about raise potential there days visitor capacity carrying Constrained growth economic preservation goals incompatible alleged satisfy help revenues maximizing policy fiscal explore model demand turn economists environmental developed being technique analysis hedonic using estimated vacations wildness application estimation Edwards Management Coastal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-26">
  <rdfs:label>
    Farber et al., Journal of Environmental Management,
    1987.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The economic value of wetlands
    systems.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Farber,S., Costanza,
    R.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The economic value of wetlands
    systems.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1987
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Environmental
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      24
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      41-51
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    systems wetlands value economic Costanza Farber Management Environmental Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-27">
  <rdfs:label>
    Farnworth et al., Interm. J. Environmental. Studies,
    1983.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Asynthesis of ecological and economic theory toward
    more complete valuation of tropical moist forest.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Farnworth, E.G., Tidrick, T.H., Smather, W.M.,
    Jordan, C.F.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Asynthesis of ecological and economic theory toward
    more complete valuation of tropical moist forest.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1983
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Interm. J. Environmental.
      Studies
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      21
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      11-28
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    forest moist tropical valuation complete more toward theory economic ecological Jordan Tidrick Farnworth
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-28">
  <rdfs:label>
    Gill, Acta Horticulturae, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The value of honeybee pollination to
    society.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Gill,R.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The value of honeybee pollination to
    society.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Acta
      Horticulturae
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      62-68
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    society pollination honeybee value Gill Acta
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-29">
  <rdfs:label>
    Godoy et al., Economic Botany, 1993.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Amethod for the economic valuation of non-timber
    tropocal forest products.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Godoy,R., Lubowski,R.,
    Markandya,A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Amethod for the economic valuation of non-timber
    tropocal forest products.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1993
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Economic Botany
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      47
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      220-223
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    By drawing on quantitative studies in social
    anthropology, zoology, ethnobotany, and economics we present a method for
    conducting an economic valuation of non-timber forest products. A review
    of 24 studies suggests that the median value for non-timber forest
    products is about $50/ha/year. We discuss problems with past studies and
    suggest ways to get better estimates of output quantities, marginal costs,
    and prices.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    prices costs marginal quantities output estimates better ways suggest studies past with problems discuss about products forest value median that suggests review valuation economic conducting method present economics ethnobotany zoology anthropology social quantitative drawing Godoy Botany Economic
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-30">
  <rdfs:label>
    Gren et al., Environmental and Resource Economics,
    1994.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Primary and secondaary values of wetlands
    ecosystems.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Gren,I.M., Folke,C. et
    al
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Primary and secondaary values of wetlands
    ecosystems.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1994
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Environmental and Resource
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      4
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      55-74
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    ecosystems wetlands values Primary Gren Economics Resource Environmental
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-31">
  <rdfs:label>
    Grimes et al., Ambio, 1994.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Valuing the Rain Forest: the economic value of
    nontimber forest products in Ecuador.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Grimes, A., Loomis, S., Jahnige,P., Burnham,M.,
    Onthank,K., Alarcon,R., Cuenca, W.P., Martinez,C.C., Neil,D., Balick, M.,
    Bennett,B., Mendelsohn,R..
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Valuing the Rain Forest: the economic value of
    nontimber forest products in Ecuador.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1994
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ambio
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      23
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      405-410
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    This study calculates the value of three ha of
    primary forest in the Upper Napo region of Amazonian Ecuador based on the
    potential extraction of nontimber forest products (NTFPs). Through
    ethnobotanical and market surveys, the annual harvest levels, market
    prices and extraction costs of seven fruits, three medicinal barks, and
    one resin are measured. The present value of net revenue from NTFP
    collection is USD 2830 in the upland plots and USD 1257 in the alluvial
    plot which is significantly higher than the returns from alternative land
    uses in this area.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    area this uses land alternative from returns than higher significantly which plot alluvial plots upland collection revenue value present measured resin barks medicinal three fruits seven costs extraction prices market levels harvest annual surveys Through products forest potential based Ecuador region Upper primary calculates study This economic Forest Rain Valuing Mendelsohn Bennett Balick Neil Martinez Cuenca Alarcon Burnham Loomis Grimes
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-32">
  <rdfs:label>
    Gupta et al., American Journal of Agricultural Economics,
    1975.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic creteriz for freshwater wetland policy in
    Massachussettss.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Gupta, T.R.,
    Forster,J.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic creteriz for freshwater wetland policy in
    Massachussettss.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1975
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      American Journal of Agricultural
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      57
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      40-45
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    policy wetland freshwater Economic Forster Gupta Economics Agricultural Journal American
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-33">
  <rdfs:label>
    Hickman, Forest Ecology and Management, 1990.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Forested-wetland trends in the United States: an
    economic perspective.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Hickman,C
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Forested-wetland trends in the United States: an
    economic perspective.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Forest Ecology and
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      33
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      227-238
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    perspective economic States United trends Hickman Management Ecology Forest
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-34">
  <rdfs:label>
    Higgins et al., Ecological Economics, 1997.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    An economical simulation model of mountain fynbos
    ecosystems: dynamics, valuation and management.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Higgins, S.I., Turpie, J.K., Costanza,R.,
    Cowling,R.W., Le Maitre, D.C., Marais, C., Midgley,
    G.F.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    An economical simulation model of mountain fynbos
    ecosystems: dynamics, valuation and management.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1997
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      22
    </documentation:series-issue>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Mountain fynbos ecosystems in South Africa are
    threatened by alien plant invasions and by a lack of funding for effective
    management of these invasions. This paper develops an ecological-economic
    argument for the effective management of plant invasions in mountain
    fynbos ecosystems. We do this by building a dynamic ecological economic
    model which values the ecosystem services that fynbos ecosystems provide
    under different management regimes. We propose that the services that
    mountain fynbos ecosystems provide fall into six components: water
    production, wildflower harvest, hiker visitation, ecotourist visitation,
    endemic species and genetic storage. A scenario analysis based on a
    hypothetical 4 km(2) mountain fynbos ecosystem in the western part of the
    fynbos biome estimated that the ecosystem's value varies from R19 million
    (under low valuation and poor management scenario) to R300 million (under
    high valuation and good management scenario) [R4.50=US$1]. Water
    production and genetic storage were the most valuable ecosystem services.
    The model showed that the cost of clearing alien plants (under the
    proactive management scenario) was a tiny (0.6-5%) proportion of the value
    of mountain fynbos ecosystems. This result motivates an injection of funds
    for clearing alien plants from mountain fynbos ecosystems. (C) 1997
    Elsevier Science B.V.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Science Elsevier ecosystems mountain from plants alien clearing funds injection motivates result This value proportion tiny management proactive cost that showed model services ecosystem valuable most were storage genetic production Water good valuation high million poor varies estimated biome part western hypothetical based analysis scenario species endemic visitation hiker harvest wildflower water components into fall provide propose regimes different under values which economic ecological dynamic building this invasions plant effective argument develops paper these funding lack threatened Africa South Mountain dynamics simulation economical Midgley Maitre Cowling Costanza Higgins Economics Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-35">
  <rdfs:label>
    Houde et al., Estuaries, 1993.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Recent trends in estuarine fisheries: predictions
    of fish production and yield.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Houde,E.D., Rutherford,
    E.S.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Recent trends in estuarine fisheries: predictions of
    fish production and yield.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1993
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Estuaries
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      16
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      161-176
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Trends in global and United States fish catches
    were examined to determine the status of estuarine fisheries yields
    relative to those from other ecosystems. Potential marine fish production,
    based upon primary production relationships, was estimated globally and
    for specific marine ecosystems, including estuaries. While global fish
    catches increased substantially during the past two decades and continued
    to increase through 1989, catches of estuarine-dependent species have
    peaked or stabilized. In the United States, total catches have increased
    but many estuarine-dependent fisheries have declined, although the
    declines in catches are no more dramatic than those of heavily-fished
    continental shelf species. Overfishing probably is the primary cause of
    declines in estuarine and shelf fisheries. A few estuarine-dependent
    species of the United States have experienced substantial increases in
    harvests since 1970, for example, Pacific salmons, menhaden, and penaeid
    shrimps. The percentage contribution of major estuarine fisheries to the
    United States commercial catch declined between 1970 and 1990, although
    the yield of these species increased substantially. Global marine
    fisheries production at trophic level 2.5 was estimated to be 1,359
    million tons. Potential yield was estimated to be 307 million tons, but
    the 1989 world marine catch was only 86.5 million tons. The major
    fraction, 196 million tons, of the estimated potential yield was for the
    open ocean where technological constraints may prevent its full
    realization. Of the remaining 111 million tons of the potential, 18.0
    million tons (16.2%) may come from estuaries and probably already is fully
    exploited. The potential catches from shelves, 68.5 million tons (61.6%),
    and upwelling areas, 24.8 million tons (22.2%), while considerably larger
    than those from estuaries, are lower in a relative sense (per unit area)
    than fisheries production and potential catch in estuarine zones.
    Relationships between fish production, fish harvest, and primary
    production were examined in specific estuaries. The developing role of
    aquaculture and its effect on estuarine fisheries are discussed
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    discussed fisheries estuarine effect aquaculture role developing estuaries specific examined were production primary harvest fish between Relationships exploited fully already probably from come tons million potential remaining realization full prevent constraints technological where ocean open yield estimated fraction major only catch marine world Potential level trophic Global substantially increased species these although declined commercial States United contribution percentage shrimps menhaden salmons Pacific example since harvests increases substantial experienced have shelf declines cause continental those than dramatic more catches many total stabilized peaked through increase continued decades past during global While including ecosystems globally relationships upon based other relative yields status determine Trends predictions trends Recent Rutherford Houde Estuaries The and its are
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-36">
  <rdfs:label>
    Howarth et al., Biogeochemistry, 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Regional nitrogen budgets and riverine N and P
    fluxes of the drainages to the North Atlantic Ocean: Natural and human
    influences.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Howarth,R.W., Billen, G., Swaney,D., Townsend,
    A., Jaworski,N., Lajtha,K., Downing, J.A., Elmgren,R., Caraco,N.,
    Jordan,T., Beremdse,F., Feemeu,J., Kudeyarov,V., Murdoch,P.,
    Zhu,Z.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Regional nitrogen budgets and riverine N and P fluxes
    of the drainages to the North Atlantic Ocean: Natural and human
    influences.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Biogeochemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      35
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      75
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    We present estimates of total nitrogen and total
    phosphorus fluxes in rivers to the North Atlantic Ocean from 14 regions in
    North America, South America, Europe, and Africa which collectively
    comprise the drainage basins to the North Atlantic. The Amazon basin
    dominates the overall phosphorus flux and has the highest phosphorus flux
    per area. The total nitrogen flux from the Amazon is also large,
    contributing 3.3 Tg yr(-1) out of a total for the entire North Atlantic
    region of 13.1 Tg yr(-1). On a per area basis, however, the largest
    nitrogen fluxes are found in the highly disturbed watersheds around the
    North Sea, in northwestern Europe, and in the northeastern U.S., all of
    which have riverine nitrogen fluxes greater than 1,000 kg N km(-2) yr(-1).
    Non-point sources of nitrogen dominate riverine fluxes to the coast in all
    regions. River fluxes of total nitrogen from the temperate regions of the
    North Atlantic basin are correlated with population density, as has been
    observed previously for fluxes of nitrate in the world's major rivers.
    However, more striking is a strong linear correlation between river fluxes
    of total nitrogen and the sum of anthropogenically-derived nitrogen inputs
    to the temperate regions (fertilizer application, human-induced increases
    in atmospheric deposition of oxidized forms of nitrogen, fixation by
    leguminous crops, and the import/export of nitrogen in agricultural
    products). On average, regional nitrogen fluxes in rivers are only 25% of
    these anthropogenically derived nitrogen inputs. Denitrification in
    wetlands and aquatic ecosystems is probably the dominant sink, with
    storage in forests perhaps also of importance. Storage of nitrogen in
    groundwater, although of importance in some localities, is a very small
    sink for nitrogen inputs in all regions. Agricultural sources of nitrogen
    dominate inputs in many regions, particularly the Mississippi basin and
    the North Sea drainages. Deposition of oxidized nitrogen, primarily of
    industrial origin, is the major control over river nitrogen export in some
    regions such as the northeastern U.S. Using data from relatively pristine
    areas as an index of change, we estimate that riverine nitrogen fluxes in
    many of the temperate regions have increased from pre-industrial times by
    2 to 20 fold, although some regions such as northern Canada are relatively
    unchanged. Fluxes from the most disturbed region, the North Sea drainages,
    have increased by 6 to 20 fold. Fluxes from the Amazon basin are also at
    least 2 to 5 fold greater than estimated fluxes from undisturbed
    temperate-zone regions, despite low population density and low inputs of
    anthropogenic nitrogen to the region. This suggests that natural riverine
    nitrogen fluxes in the tropics may be significantly greater than in the
    temperate zone. However, deforestation may be contributing to the tropical
    fluxes. In either case, projected increases in fertilizer use and
    atmospheric deposition in the coming decades are likely to cause dramatic
    increases in nitrogen loading to many tropical river systems.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    systems river tropical many loading nitrogen increases dramatic cause likely decades coming deposition atmospheric fertilizer projected case either fluxes contributing deforestation However zone temperate than greater significantly tropics riverine natural that suggests This region anthropogenic inputs density population despite regions undisturbed from estimated fold least also basin Amazon Fluxes increased have drainages North disturbed most northeastern such some export over control major origin industrial primarily oxidized Deposition Mississippi particularly dominate sources Agricultural sink small localities importance although groundwater Storage perhaps forests storage with dominant probably ecosystems aquatic wetlands Denitrification derived these only rivers regional average agricultural crops leguminous fixation forms application total between correlation linear strong striking more world's nitrate previously observed been correlated Atlantic River coast which Europe northwestern around watersheds highly found largest however basis area entire large flux phosphorus highest overall dominates basins drainage comprise collectively Africa America South Ocean estimates present influences human Natural budgets Regional Murdoch Jordan Downing Jaworski Townsend Swaney Billen Howarth Biogeochemistry
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-37">
  <rdfs:label>
    Ihori et al., Soil Science Society of American Journal,
    1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Effects of cultivation and abandonment on soil
    organic matter in northeastern Colorado.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Ihori,T.,Burke,I.C., Lauenroth, W.K.,
    Coffin,D.P.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Effects of cultivation and abandonment on soil
    organic matter in northeastern Colorado.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Science Society of American
      Journal
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      59
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1112-1119
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The influence of climate and soil texture on soil
    organic matter losses due to cultivation are rarely addressed due to lack
    of appropriately paired sites. In addition, soil organic matter recovery
    on previously cultivated fields is not well understood. In this study, we
    identified seven sites that have native and abandoned fields and five
    sites that have native, abandoned, and cultivated fields. All sites are in
    the northeastern Colorado shortgrass steppe, crossing a precipitation
    range from 320 to 370 mm, and have sand contents from 36 to 67%.
    Historical cultivation reduced soil C and N across this region by between
    16 and 42%. Although variation in native soil C and N at these sites
    correlates with climate and soil texture, variation among sites in soil
    losses due to cultivation is not explained by these variables. We used a
    statistical model and a simulation model to estimate patterns of soil loss
    across sites; neither model predicted variation among sites adequately (P
    &gt; 0.05). We suggest that local-scale variability in organic matter
    losses due to cultivation are strongly dependent on management practices.
    With a simulation model and the data from native, abandoned, and
    cultivated fields, we estimated that 25 to 120 g C m(-2) have been
    recovered on the abandoned fields during the past 50 yr. Such rates of
    recovery are small compared with loss rates due to cultivation. Rates of
    soil organic matter recovery are constrained by natural pedogenic
    processes, which cannot reverse disturbance processes at a comparable rate
    in this semiarid environment.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    environment semiarid this rate comparable processes disturbance reverse cannot which pedogenic natural constrained recovery matter organic soil Rates cultivation rates loss with compared small Such past during fields abandoned recovered that estimated cultivated native from data model simulation With practices management dependent strongly losses variability suggest adequately sites among variation predicted neither across patterns estimate statistical used variables these explained texture climate correlates Although between region reduced Historical contents sand have range precipitation crossing steppe Colorado northeastern five seven identified study understood well previously addition paired appropriately lack addressed rarely influence abandonment Effects Coffin Lauenroth Burke Journal American Society Science Soil
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-38">
  <rdfs:label>
    Jones et al., Journal of Soil and Water Conservation,
    1985.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Runoff, soil and nutrient losses from rangeland and
    dry-farmed cropland in the southern high plain.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Jones,O.R.,Eck,H.V., Smith, S.J., Coleman,G.A.,
    Hauser,V.L.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Runoff, soil and nutrient losses from rangeland and
    dry-farmed cropland in the southern high plain.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1985
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Soil and Water
      Conservation
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      1
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      161-164
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    plain high southern cropland rangeland from losses nutrient soil Runoff Hauser Coleman Smith Jones Conservation Water Soil Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-39">
  <rdfs:label>
    Lant et al., Environment and Planning, 1990.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Greenbelts in the cornbelt: riparian wetlands,
    instrinsic values and market failure.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Lant,C.L., Roberts,
    R.S.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Greenbelts in the cornbelt: riparian wetlands,
    instrinsic values and market failure.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Environment and
      Planning
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      22
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1375-1388
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    failure market values wetlands riparian Roberts Lant Planning Environment
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-40">
  <rdfs:label>
    Lynne et al., Journal of Enviromental Economics and Management,
    1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic valuation of marsh areas to marine
    production processes.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Lynne, G.D., Conroy,P.D.,
    Pochasta,F.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic valuation of marsh areas to marine
    production processes.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Enviromental Economics and
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      8
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      175-186
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    processes production marine areas marsh valuation Economic Conroy Lynne Management Economics Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-41">
  <rdfs:label>
    Mattews, Journal of Climate and Applied Meteorology,
    1983.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Global vegetation and land-use: new high-resolution
    data bases for climatic studies.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Mattews, E.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Global vegetation and land-use: new high-resolution
    data bases for climatic studies.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1983
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Climate and Applied
      Meteorology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      22
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      474-487
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    studies climatic bases data resolution high land vegetation Global Mattews Meteorology Applied Climate Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-42">
  <rdfs:label>
    Moister et al., Nature, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Methane and nitrous oxide fluxes in native,
    fertilized and cultivated grassland.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Moister, A.D., Schimel,d., Valentine,D.,
    Bronson,K., Parton,W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Methane and nitrous oxide fluxes in native,
    fertilized and cultivated grassland.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      330-332
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    grassland cultivated fertilized native fluxes oxide nitrous Methane Parton Bronson Valentine Schimel Moister Nature
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-43">
  <rdfs:label>
    Nixon et al., Biogeochemistry, 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The fate of nitrogen and phosphorus at the land-sea
    margin of the North Atlantic Ocean.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Nixon,S.W., Ammerman,J.W., Atkinson,L.P.,
    Berounsky,V.M., Billen,G., Boicourt,W.C., Boynton,W.R., Church,T.M.,
    DiToro,D.M., Elmgren,r., Garber,J.H., Giblin,A.E., Jahnke, R.A.,Owens,
    N.J.P., Pilson,M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The fate of nitrogen and phosphorus at the land-sea
    margin of the North Atlantic Ocean.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Biogeochemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      35
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      141
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Five large rivers that discharge on the western
    North Atlantic continental shelf carry about 45% of the nitrogen (N) and
    70% of the phosphorus (P) that others estimate to be the total flux of
    these elements from the entire North Atlantic watershed, including North,
    Central and South America, Europe, and Northwest Africa. We estimate that
    61 . 10(9) moles y(-1) of N and 20 . 10(9) moles y(-1) of P from the large
    rivers are buried with sediments in their deltas, and that an equal amount
    of N and P from the large rivers is lost to the shelf through burial of
    river sediments that are deposited directly on the continental slope. The
    effective transport of active N and P from land to the shelf through the
    very large rivers is thus reduced to 292 . 10(9) moles y(-1) of N and 13 .
    10(9) moles y(-1) of P. The remaining riverine fluxes from land must pass
    through estuaries. An analysis of annual total N and total P budgets for
    various estuaries around the North Atlantic revealed that the net
    fractional transport of these nutrients through estuaries to the
    continental shelf is inversely correlated with the log mean residence time
    of water in the system. This is consistent with numerous observations of
    nutrient retention and loss in temperate lakes. Denitrification is the
    major process responsible for removing N in most estuaries, and the
    fraction of total N input that is denitrified appears to be directly
    proportional to the log mean water residence time. In general, we estimate
    that estuarine processes retain and remove 30-65% of the total N and
    10-55% of the total P that would otherwise pass into the coastal ocean.
    The resulting transport through estuaries to the shelf amounts to 172-335
    . 10(9) moles y(-1) of N and 11-19 . 10(9) moles y(-1) of P. These values
    are similar to the effective contribution from the large rivers that
    discharge directly on the shelf. For the North Atlantic shelf as a whole,
    N fluxes from major rivers and estuaries exceed atmospheric deposition by
    a factor of 3.5-4.7, but this varies widely among regions of the shelf.
    For example, on the U.S. Atlantic shelf and on the northwest European
    shelf, atmospheric deposition of N may exceed estuarine exports.
    Denitrification in shelf sediments exceeds the combined N input from land
    and atmosphere by a factor of 1.4-2.2. This deficit must be met by a flux
    of N from the deeper ocean. Burial of organic matter fixed on the shelf
    removes only a small fraction of the total N and P input (2-12% of N from
    land and atmosphere; 1-17% of P), but it may be a significant loss for P
    in the North Sea and some other regions. The removal of N and P in
    fisheries landings is very small. The gross exchange of N and P between
    the shelf and the open ocean is much lager than inputs from land and, for
    the North Atlantic shelf as a whole, it may be much larger than the N and
    P removed through denitrification, burial, and fisheries. Overall, the
    North Atlantic continental shelf appears to remove some 700-950 . 10(9)
    moles of N each year from the deep ocean and to transport somewhere
    between 18 and 30 . 10(9) moles of P to the open sea. If the N and P
    associated with riverine sediments deposited on the continental slope are
    included in the total balance, the net flux of N to the shelf is reduced
    by 60 . 10(9) moles y(-1) and the P flux to the ocean is increased by 20 .
    10(9) moles y(-1). These conclusions are quite tentative. however, because
    of large uncertainties in our estimates of some important terms in the
    shelf mass balance.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    balance mass shelf terms important some estimates uncertainties large because however tentative quite conclusions These increased ocean flux moles reduced total included slope continental deposited sediments riverine with associated open between somewhere transport remove appears Atlantic North Overall small very landings fisheries removal deeper from must deficit factor atmosphere land input combined exceeds Denitrification exports estuarine exceed deposition atmospheric European northwest example regions among widely varies estuaries rivers major fluxes whole directly discharge that contribution effective similar values amounts through resulting coastal into pass otherwise would retain processes estimate general lakes temperate loss retention nutrient observations numerous consistent This system water time residence mean correlated inversely nutrients these fractional revealed around various budgets annual analysis remaining thus active river burial lost amount equal deltas their buried Africa Northwest Europe America South Central including watershed entire elements others phosphorus nitrogen about carry western Five Ocean margin fate Pilson Owens Jahnke Giblin Garber Church Boynton Boicourt Billen Atkinson Ammerman Nixon Biogeochemistry
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-44">
  <rdfs:label>
    Oesterheld et al., Nature, 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Effect of animal husbandry on herbivore carrying
    capacity at a regional scale.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Oesterheld,M., Sala,O.E., McNaughton,
    S.J.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Effect of animal husbandry on herbivore carrying
    capacity at a regional scale.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      234-236
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    ALL significant properties of the herbivore
    trophic level, including biomass, consumption and productivity, are
    significantly correlated with primary productivity across a broad range of
    terrestrial ecosystems 1,2. Here we show that livestock biomass in South
    American agricultural ecosystems across a 25-fold gradient of primary
    productivity exhibited a relationship with a slope essentially identical
    to unmanaged ecosystems, but with a substantially greater y-intercept.
    Therefore the biomass of herbivores supported per unit of primary
    productivity is about an order of magnitude greater in agricultural than
    in natural ecosystems, for a given level of primary production. We also
    present evidence of an increase in livestock body size with primary
    productivity, a pattern previously characterized in natural ecosystems 3.
    To our knowledge this is the first quantitative documentation at a
    regional scale of the impact of animal husbandry practices, such as
    herding, stock selection and veterinary care, on the biomass and
    size-structure of livestock herds compared with native herbivores
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    native with compared herds livestock biomass care veterinary selection stock herding such practices husbandry animal impact scale regional documentation quantitative first this knowledge ecosystems natural characterized previously pattern productivity primary size body increase evidence present also production level given than agricultural greater magnitude order about unit supported Therefore substantially unmanaged identical essentially slope relationship exhibited gradient across American South that show Here terrestrial range broad correlated significantly consumption including trophic herbivore properties significant capacity carrying Effect Sala our the and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-45">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pauly et al., Nature, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Primary production required to sustain global
    fishersies.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pauly,D.,
    Christensen,V.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Primary production required to sustain global
    fishersies.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      255-257
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    THE mean of reported annual world fisheries
    catches for 1988-1991 (94.3 million t) was split into 39 species groups,
    to which fractional trophic levels, ranging from 1.0 (edible algae) to 4.2
    (tunas), were assigned, based on 48 published trophic models, providing a
    global coverage of six major aquatic ecosystem types. The primary
    production required to sustain each group of species was then computed
    based on a mean energy transfer efficiency between trophic levels of 10%,
    a value that was re-estimated rather than assumed. The primary production
    required to sustain the reported catches, plus 27 million t of discarded
    bycatch, amounted to 8.0% of global aquatic primary production, nearly
    four times the previous estimate. By ecosystem type, the requirements were
    only 2% for open ocean systems, but ranged from 24 to 35% in fresh water,
    upwelling and shelf systems, justifying current concerns for
    sustainability and biodiversity.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    biodiversity sustainability concerns current justifying systems shelf water fresh from ranged ocean open only were requirements type ecosystem estimate previous times four nearly production primary aquatic global amounted discarded million plus catches reported sustain required assumed than rather that value levels trophic between efficiency transfer energy based computed then species group each types major coverage providing models published assigned ranging fractional which groups into split fisheries world annual mean Primary Christensen Pauly Nature
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-46">
  <rdfs:label>
    Peters et al., Nature, 1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Valuation of an Amazonian Rain
    Forest
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Peters,C.M., Genrty,A.H.,
    Mendelsohn,R.O.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Valuation of an Amazonian Rain
    Forest
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      655-656
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Forest Rain Valuation Mendelsohn Peters Nature
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-47">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pielke et al., Ecological Applications, 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Use of USGS-provided data to improve weather and
    climate simulations.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pielke,R.A., Lee,T.J., Copeland, J.H.,
    Eastman,J.L., Ziegler,C.L., Finley,C.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Use of USGS-provided data to improve weather and
    climate simulations.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Applications
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      7
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      3
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    This paper utilizes United States Geological
    Survey (USGS) data to investigate the influence of landscape structure on
    atmospheric circulations. The procedure to insert this data in the
    Regional Atmospheric Modeling System (RAMS) is described. Simulations are
    presented for a monthly simulation of summer weather in the United States,
    for case studies of cumulonimbus convection along a dryline in the Great
    Plains of the U.S. and over northern Georgia, and for pollutant dispersal
    in South Carolina. These results demonstrate the significant role that
    landscape, including its spatial heterogeneity, has on weather and
    climate. Environmental policy-makers need to consider this feedback to
    weather and climate, rather than just assuming the atmosphere is an
    external factor to such issues as ecosystem management and water resource
    management. This feedback between the atmosphere and the land surface
    needs to be considered on all spatial scales from the plot scale to the
    global scale. This includes studies being performed at the Long-Term
    Ecological Research (LTER) sites that have been established throughout the
    United States. This paper also demonstrates the value of the USGS data in
    weather and climate simulations
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    simulations climate weather data USGS value demonstrates also paper This States United throughout established been have that sites Research Ecological performed being studies includes scale global plot from scales spatial considered needs surface land atmosphere between feedback management resource water ecosystem issues such factor external assuming just than rather this consider need Environmental heterogeneity including landscape role significant demonstrate results These Carolina South dispersal pollutant Georgia northern over Plains Great along convection cumulonimbus case summer simulation monthly presented Simulations described System Modeling Atmospheric Regional insert procedure circulations atmospheric structure influence investigate Survey Geological utilizes improve Finley Ziegler Eastman Copeland Applications the and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-48">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pimentel et al., Science, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Environmental and economic costs of soil erosion
    and conservation benefits.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pimentel,D., Harvey,C., Resosudarmo,P.,
    Sinclair,K., Kurz,D., McNair,M., Crist,S., Sphpritz,P., Fitton,L.,
    Saffouri,R., Blair,R.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Environmental and economic costs of soil erosion and
    conservation benefits.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Science
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1117-1123
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Soil erosion is a major environmental threat to the
    sustainability and productive capacity of agriculture. During the last 40
    years, nearly one-third of the world's arable land has been lost by
    erosion and continues to be lost at a rate of more than 10 million
    hectares per year. With the addition of a quarter of a million people each
    day, the world population's food demand is increasing at a time when per
    capita food productivity is beginning to decline.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    decline beginning productivity food capita increasing demand world each people million quarter addition With year hectares than more rate lost continues erosion been land arable world's nearly years last During agriculture capacity productive sustainability threat environmental major Soil benefits conservation soil costs economic Environmental Blair Fitton Crist Kurz Sinclair Harvey Pimentel Science
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-49">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pinedo-Vasques et al., Ecological Economics, 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic returns from forest conversion in the
    Peruvian Amazon.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pinedo-Vasques,M.,
    Jip,D.Z.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic returns from forest conversion in the
    Peruvian Amazon.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      76-78
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Amazon Peruvian conversion forest from returns Economic Economics Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-50">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pope et al., Journal of Environmental Management.,
    1990.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Value of wilderness designation in
    Utah.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pope,C.A., Jones,J.W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Value of wilderness designation in
    Utah.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Environmental
      Management.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      30
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      157-174
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Utah designation wilderness Value Jones Pope Management Environmental Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-51">
  <rdfs:label>
    Robinson et al., American Bee Journal, 1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The value of honey bees as pollinators of US
    crops.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Robinson,W.E., Nowogrodzki,R.,
    Morse,R.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The value of honey bees as pollinators of US
    crops.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      American Bee
      Journal
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      477-487
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    crops bees honey value Morse Robinson Journal American
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-52">
  <rdfs:label>
    Ryther, Science, 1969.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Photosynthesis and fish production in the
    sea.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Ryther,J.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Photosynthesis and fish production in the
    sea.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1969
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Science
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      72-76
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    production fish Photosynthesis Ryther Science
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-53">
  <rdfs:label>
    Sala et al., Ecology, 1988.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Primary production of the central grassland region
    o f the United States.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Sala,O.E., Parton,W.J., Joyce,L.A.,
    Lauenroth,W.K.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Primary production of the central grassland region o
    f the United States.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1988
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      69
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      40-45
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    States United region grassland central production Primary Lauenroth Joyce Parton Sala Ecology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-54">
  <rdfs:label>
    Southwick et al., Journal of Economic Entomology,
    1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Estimating the economic value of honey bees
    (Hymenoptera:Apidae) as agricultural pollinators in the United
    States.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Southwick, E.E.,
    Southwich,Lawrence,Jr.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Estimating the economic value of honey bees
    (Hymenoptera:Apidae) as agricultural pollinators in the United
    States.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Economic
      Entomology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      85
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      622-633
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The economic gains due to honey bee (Apis mellifera
    L.) agricultural pollination are evaluated. The method of analysis focuses
    on the gains to consumers through lower prices for crops that are
    benefited by honey bees. Economic demand functions for the major
    agricultural crops that are pollinated by bees are estimated. The amounts
    by which the yields of pollinated crops are increased are estimated from a
    variety of sources. In the final step, the surplus realized by consumers
    of these crops that would be lost if honey bees were depleted is
    determined. The annual social gains are estimated to range between $1.6
    and $5.7 billion.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    billion between range estimated gains social annual determined depleted were bees honey lost would that crops these consumers realized surplus step final sources variety from increased pollinated yields which amounts agricultural major functions demand Economic benefited prices lower through focuses analysis method evaluated pollination economic States United value Estimating Lawrence Southwick Entomology Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-55">
  <rdfs:label>
    Spurgeon et al., Marine Pollution Bulletin, 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The economic valution of coral
    reefs.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Spurgeon,J.P.G.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The economic valution of coral
    reefs.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Marine Pollution
      Bulletin
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      24
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      529-536
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    reefs coral economic Spurgeon Bulletin Pollution Marine
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-56">
  <rdfs:label>
    Stroud et al., Sport Fishing Inst. Bull., 1970.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Estuary Values.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Stroud, R.H.,
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Estuary Values.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1970
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Sport Fishing Inst.
      Bull.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      7-8
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Values Estuary Stroud Fishing Sport
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-57">
  <rdfs:label>
    Thibodeau et al., Journal of Environmental Managmement,
    1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    An Economic analysis of wetland
    protection
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Thibodeau, F.R.,
    Ostro,B.D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    An Economic analysis of wetland
    protection
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Environmental
      Managmement
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      12
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      19-30
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    protection wetland analysis Economic Thibodeau Environmental Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-58">
  <rdfs:label>
    Tobias et al., Ambio, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Valuing ecotourism in a tropical
    rainforest.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Tobias, A.H., Wood,
    S.E.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Valuing ecotourism in a tropical
    rainforest.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ambio
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      20
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      91-93
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    rainforest tropical Valuing Wood Tobias
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-60">
  <rdfs:label>
    Fankhauser et al., The economics of climate change. Proceedings
    of an OECD/IEA Conference., 1994.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The social costs of greenhouse gas
    emissions.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Fankhauser,S.,
    Pearce,D.W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The social costs of greenhouse gas
    emissions.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1994
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      The economics of climate change. Proceedings
      of an OECD/IEA Conference.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      71-86
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    emissions greenhouse costs social Pearce Fankhauser Conference Proceedings change climate economics
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-61">
  <rdfs:label>
    Brown et al., The economics of project appraisal and the
    environment., 1994.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The economic value of non-marked benefits of
    tropical forests:carbon storage.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Brown,K., Pearce,
    D.W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The economic value of non-marked benefits of tropical
    forests:carbon storage.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1994
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      The economics of project appraisal and the
      environment.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      102-123
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    storage carbon forests tropical benefits value economic Pearce Brown environment appraisal project economics
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-62">
  <rdfs:label>
    Cowling et al., Nature's Services., 1997.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Services supplied by South African fynbos
    ecosystems.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Cowling,R.M., Costanza,R.,
    Higgins,S.I.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Services supplied by South African fynbos
    ecosystems.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1997
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature's
      Services.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    ecosystems African South supplied Services Higgins Costanza Cowling Nature's
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-63">
  <rdfs:label>
    de Groot, Functions of nature: evaluation of nature in
    environmental planning, management and decision making., 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Funtions and values of the Dutch Wadden
    Sea
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    de Groot,R.S.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Funtions and values of the Dutch Wadden
    Sea
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Functions of nature: evaluation of nature in
      environmental planning, management and decision
      making.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      197-217
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Wadden Dutch values Groot making decision management planning environmental nature evaluation Functions Sea
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-64">
  <rdfs:label>
    Foster, Wetland functions and values: the state of our
    understanding., 1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Measuring the social value of wetland
    benefits.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Foster,J.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Measuring the social value of wetland
    benefits.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Wetland functions and values: the state of
      our understanding.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      84-92
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    benefits wetland value social Measuring Foster understanding state values functions Wetland
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-65">
  <rdfs:label>
    Holland et al., The chemistry of the atmosphere and oceans.,
    1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Holland et al., The chemistry of the atmosphere and oceans.,
    1978.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Holland, H. D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The chemistry of the atmosphere and oceans.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      The chemistry of the atmosphere and
      oceans.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      351
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    oceans atmosphere chemistry Holland
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-66">
  <rdfs:label>
    Kramer et al., Managing the world's forests: looking for balance
    between conservation and development., 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Forest valuation.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Kramer,R.A.,Healy,R.,
    Mendelsohn,R.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Forest valuation.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Managing the world's forests: looking for
      balance between conservation and
      development.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    valuation Forest Mendelsohn Healy Kramer development conservation between balance looking forests world's Managing
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-67">
  <rdfs:label>
    Lampietti et al., Environmental Economics., 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Human influence on
    biodiversity.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Lampietti,J.A.,
    Dixon,J.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Human influence on
    biodiversity.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Environmental
      Economics.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:working-paper
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    biodiversity influence Human Dixon Economics Environmental
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-68">
  <rdfs:label>
    Mori, Sustainable harvesting and marketing of rain forest
    products., 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The Brazil nut industry: past,present and
    future.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Mori,S.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The Brazil nut industry: past,present and
    future.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Sustainable harvesting and marketing of rain
      forest products.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    future present past industry Brazil Mori products forest rain marketing harvesting Sustainable
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-69">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pearce, Economic policy toward the environment.,
    1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    An economic approach to saving the tropical
    forests.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pearce,D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    An economic approach to saving the tropical
    forests.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Economic policy toward the
      environment.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      239-262
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    forests tropical saving approach economic Pearce environment toward policy Economic
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-70">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pimental, Techniques for reducing pesticides-environmental an
    economic benefits., 0.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Pest management in
    agriculture.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pimental,D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Pest management in agriculture.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Techniques for reducing
      pesticides-environmental an economic
      benefits.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    agriculture management Pest Pimental benefits economic reducing Techniques
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-71">
  <rdfs:label>
    Postel et al., Nature's services, 1997.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Freshwater ecosystem
    services.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Postel,S.,
    Carpenter,S.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Freshwater ecosystem services.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1997
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature's services
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      195-214
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    services ecosystem Freshwater Carpenter Postel Nature's
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-72">
  <rdfs:label>
    Sala et al., Ecosystem services., 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Ecosystem services in
    grasslands.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Sala,O.E.,
    Paruelo,J.M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Ecosystem services in
    grasslands.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecosystem
      services.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    grasslands services Ecosystem Sala
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-73">
  <rdfs:label>
    Schlesinger, Biogeochemistry: an analysis of global change.,
    1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The Sea.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Schlesinger,W.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The Sea.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Biogeochemistry: an analysis of global
      change.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      254-293
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Schlesinger change global analysis Biogeochemistry
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-74">
  <rdfs:label>
    Shiklomanov, Water in crisis: a guide to the World's fresh water
    resources., 1993.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    World fresh water
    resources.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Shiklomanov,L.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    World fresh water resources.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1993
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Water in crisis: a guide to the World's fresh
      water resources.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      13-24
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    resources water fresh World World's guide crisis Water
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-75">
  <rdfs:label>
    Schlesinger, Biogeochemistry, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The Global Carbon Cycle
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Schlesinger,W.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The Global Carbon Cycle
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Biogeochemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      308-321
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Cycle Carbon Global Schlesinger Biogeochemistry The
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-77">
  <rdfs:label>
    Adger et al., Global Environmental Change Series,
    1994.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Towards estimating total economic value of forest
    in Mexico.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Adger,N., Brown,K., Cerigni,R.,
    Moran,D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Towards estimating total economic value of forest in
    Mexico.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1994
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Global Environmental Change
      Series
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:working-paper
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Mexico forest value economic total estimating Towards Moran Brown Adger Series Change Environmental Global
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-78">
  <rdfs:label>
    Lampietti et al., Environmental Economics, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    To see the forest for the Trees: a guide to
    non-timber forest benefits.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Lampietti,J.A.,
    Dixon,J.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    To see the forest for the Trees: a guide to
    non-timber forest benefits.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Environmental
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    benefits forest guide Trees Dixon Economics Environmental
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-79">
  <rdfs:label>
    Adger et al., Global Environmental Change Series,
    1994.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Towards estimating total economic valueof forests
    in Mexico
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Adger,N.,
    Brown,K.,Cervigni,R.,Moran,D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Towards estimating total economic valueof forests in
    Mexico
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1994
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Global Environmental Change
      Series
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1-41
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Mexico forests economic total estimating Towards Moran Brown Adger Series Change Environmental Global
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-90">
  <rdfs:label>
    Schroth et al., Agriculture Ecosystems and Environment,
    1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Subsoil accumulation of mineral nitrogen under
    polyculture and monoculture plantations, fallow and primary forest in a
    ferralitic Amazonia upland soil
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Schroth, Gotz; Ferreira Da Silva, Luciana;
    Seixas, Rosangela; Teixeira, Wenceslau Geraldes; Macaeda, Jeferson L.V.;
    Zech, Wolfgang
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Subsoil accumulation of mineral nitrogen under
    polyculture and monoculture plantations, fallow and primary forest in a
    ferralitic Amazonia upland soil
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Agriculture Ecosystems and
      Environment
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      75
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      109-120
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Central Amazonia is characterized by high and
    intensive rainfall and permeable soils. When rainforests are cleared for
    agricultural use, the efficient nutrient recycling mechanisms of the
    forests are disrupted and the nutrient availability in the topsoil is
    increased by fertilization, thereby increasing the potential for nutrient
    leaching. In this study, the distribution of mineral N in the upper two
    meters of a ferralitic upland soil was evaluated as an indicator for
    nutrient leaching and for the potential contribution of the subsoil to
    crop nutrition. A perennial polyculture system with four tree crops and a
    leguminous cover crop at two fertilization levels was compared with a
    monoculture plantation of peach palm (Bactris gasipaes), spontaneous
    fallow and primary rainforest. Mineral N accumulated principally as
    nitrate in the subsoil under all agricultural crops and also under the
    primary forest, although to a lesser extent. Within the polyculture
    system, there were significant differences in N accumulation between the
    tree crop species, and for one of the species (Theobroma grandiflorum)
    also between fertilization levels. The principal sources of subsoil N were
    mineral fertilizer and presumably N from the mineralization of leguminous
    biomass and soil organic matter. The N losses from the agricultural
    systems and the absence of yield responses of the tree crops to N
    fertilization indicated that agricultural production was not limited by N
    at this site, or that N was too rapidly leached to be taken up efficiently
    by the crops. None of the tree crop species seemed to be efficient in
    capturing leached N, Strategies are discussed for reducing N losses from
    agricultural systems with perennial crops, including the development of
    site- and species-specific fertilizer recommendations, closer tree
    spacing, and the encouragement of lateral and vertical tree root
    development
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    development root tree vertical lateral encouragement spacing closer recommendations fertilizer including crops perennial with systems agricultural from losses reducing discussed Strategies leached capturing efficient seemed species crop None efficiently taken rapidly that site this limited production indicated fertilization responses yield absence matter organic soil biomass leguminous mineralization presumably mineral were subsoil sources principal levels between also accumulation differences significant there system Within extent lesser although forest primary under nitrate principally accumulated Mineral rainforest fallow spontaneous palm peach plantation monoculture compared cover four nutrition contribution potential leaching nutrient indicator evaluated upland meters upper distribution study increasing thereby increased topsoil availability disrupted forests mechanisms recycling cleared When soils permeable rainfall intensive high characterized Amazonia Central plantations nitrogen Subsoil Wolfgang Zech Geraldes Teixeira Luciana Silva Ferreira Schroth Environment Ecosystems Agriculture the are for and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-93">
  <rdfs:label>
    Wilsey et al., Ecology, 2000.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Biodiversity and ecosystem functioning: importance
    of species evenness in an old field
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Wilsey, B.J., Potvin,
    C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Biodiversity and ecosystem functioning: importance of
    species evenness in an old field
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2000
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      81
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      887-892
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Changes in land use, habitat fragmentation,
    nutrient enrichment, and environmental stress often lead to reduced plant
    diversity in ecosystems. However, it remains controversial whether these
    reductions in diversity will affect energy flow and nutrient cycling.
    Diversity has two components: species richness, or the number of plant
    species in a given area, and species evenness, or how well distributed
    abundance or biomass is among species within a community. We
    experimentally varied species evenness and the identity of the dominant
    plant species in an old field of Quebec to test whether plant productivity
    would increase with increasing levels of evenness, and whether
    relationships would be invariant with respect to species identity. Total
    and belowground biomass increased linearly with increasing levels of
    evenness after one growing season. These relationships did not depend on
    the identity of the dominant species. Relationships between aboveground
    biomass and evenness varied and depended on the identity of the dominant.
    Our results are largely consistent with the idea that human-influenced
    reductions in small-scale plant diversity, in this case evenness, will
    lead to indirect reductions in total primary productivity. Furthermore,
    because the evenness treatments were not confounded with species identity,
    our results suggest that diversity has an effect on plant productivity
    above and beyond the sampling effect (having a higher probability of
    species with higher growth rates in diverse communities) seen in studies
    that vary species richness.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    richness species vary that studies seen diverse rates growth higher with probability effect sampling beyond above productivity plant diversity suggest results identity confounded were treatments evenness because Furthermore primary total reductions indirect lead will case this idea consistent largely dominant depended varied biomass aboveground between Relationships depend relationships These season growing after levels increasing linearly increased belowground Total respect invariant would whether increase test Quebec field experimentally community within among abundance distributed well area given number components Diversity cycling nutrient flow energy affect these controversial remains However ecosystems reduced often stress environmental enrichment fragmentation habitat land Changes importance functioning ecosystem Biodiversity Potvin Wilsey Ecology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-94">
  <rdfs:label>
    Scurlock et al., Global Change Biology, 2002.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Estimating net primary productivity from grassland
    biomass dynamics measurements
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Scurlock, J.M.O., Johnson, K., Olson, J.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Estimating net primary productivity from grassland
    biomass dynamics measurements
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2002
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Global Change
      Biology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      8
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      736-753
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    To address the need for a high quality data set
    based upon field observations suitable for parameterization, calibration,
    and validation of terrestrial biosphere models, we have developed a
    comprehensive global database on net primary productivity (NPP). We have
    compiled field measurements of biomass and associated environmental data
    for multiple study sites in major grassland types worldwide. Where
    sufficient data were available, we compared aboveground and total NPP
    estimated by six computational methods (algorithms) for 31 grassland
    sites. As has been found previously, NPP estimates were 2-5 times higher
    using methods which accounted for the dynamics of dead matter, compared
    with what is still the most commonly applied estimate of NPP (maximum peak
    live biomass). It is suggested that assumptions such as the use of peak
    biomass as an indicator of NPP in grasslands may apply only within certain
    subbiomes, e.g. temperate steppe grasslands. Additional data on
    belowground dynamics, or other reliable estimates of belowground
    productivity, are required if grasslands are to be fully appreciated for
    their role in the global carbon cycle.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    cycle carbon global role their appreciated fully grasslands required productivity belowground estimates reliable other dynamics data Additional steppe temperate certain within only apply indicator biomass peak such assumptions that suggested live estimate applied commonly most still what with compared matter dead accounted which methods using higher times were previously found been sites grassland computational estimated total aboveground available sufficient Where worldwide types major study multiple environmental associated measurements field compiled have primary database comprehensive developed models biosphere terrestrial validation calibration parameterization suitable observations upon based quality high need address from Estimating Olson Johnson Scurlock Biology Change Global
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-96">
  <rdfs:label>
    et al., Ecological Society of America, 1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    "With-in Stand Nutrient Cycling in Artic and Boreal
    Wetlands"
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Sven Jonasson; Gaius R.
    Shaver
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    "With-in Stand Nutrient Cycling in Artic and Boreal
    Wetlands"
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological Society of
      America
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      80
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      2139
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The aims of this article are to characterize the
    nutrient regime in arctic and boreal wetlands and to review published data
    on various aspects of within-stand nutrient-cycling. Most northern
    wetlands, such as boreal and arctic ombrogenous bogs and most arctic mesic
    and wet ecosystem types, are poor in inorganic, plant-available nutrients
    because mineralization is restricted due to low temperatures and anoxic
    soils. This is particularly true in the Arctic because nutrient inputs
    from external sources quite often are small, and nutrient pools in the
    vegetation also are small. By contrast, the soil and the microbial biomass
    often contain large stocks of organically fixed nutrients that are largely
    unavailable to plants. The vegetation is adapted to the low availability
    of nutrients by the perennial nature of both entire plants and plant
    tissues, which minimizes the annual nutrient losses and reduces the demand
    for nutrient uptake to produce new tissues. Furthermore, many of the
    dominant plant life-forms can use soil organic nitrogen (N), either by
    direct uptake or through connections with ericoid or ectotrophic
    mycorrhizae, which reduces competition from other plant groups without the
    ability to utilize organic N.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    organic utilize ability without groups plant other from competition reduces which ectotrophic with connections through uptake direct either nitrogen soil dominant many Furthermore tissues produce nutrient demand losses annual minimizes plants entire both nature perennial nutrients availability adapted vegetation unavailable largely that fixed organically stocks large contain often biomass microbial contrast small also pools quite sources external inputs because Arctic true particularly This soils anoxic temperatures restricted mineralization inorganic poor types ecosystem mesic arctic most bogs boreal such wetlands northern Most aspects various data published review regime characterize article this aims Wetlands Boreal Artic Cycling Nutrient Stand Shaver Gaius America Society Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-97">
  <rdfs:label>
    Nicolas Maire et al., Soil Biology and Biochemistry,
    1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    "Organic matter cycling in grassland soils of the
    Swiss Jura mountains: biodiversity and strategies of the living
    communities"
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Nicolas Maire, Daniel Borcard, Endre Laczko,
    Willy Matthey
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    "Organic matter cycling in grassland soils of the
    Swiss Jura mountains: biodiversity and strategies of the living
    communities"
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Biology and
      Biochemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      31
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1281-1293
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Several characteristics of the soils of three
    nutrient-poor grasslands, pertaining to their biological activity, have
    been measured three times during the vegetation cycle of 1994 in the Swiss
    Jura. Properties measured were: abundances of the faunal groups Collembola
    (Insecta), Oribatida, Gamasida and Actinedida (Acarina); PLFA richness,
    abundance and diversity (indicating microbial diversity); ATP content (an
    index of soil biomass), soil respiration (CO2 production); and alkaline
    phosphatase, urease, chitinase, xylanase and laminarinase activities, as
    biochemical tracers of biotic activity. Most of these variables showed
    significant differences from site to site. In particular, the biochemical
    descriptors ATP content and phosphatase and urease activities varied in
    accordance with the amount of the clay-humic complex. The soils showed two
    strategies of litter degradation: (a) an enzymatic strategy, prevailing at
    the end of winter, when the edaphic climate is unfavourable; (b) a biotic
    strategy, based upon the work of the whole living community (fauna and
    microflora), at its maximum at the end of summer. Diversity of the
    microbial communities (as estimated by the PLFA richness) was highest in
    spring, when the carbon sources are complex (young litter), and
    subsequently decreased in inverse relationship with the specific activity
    of the biomass (viz, CO2 production-to-ATP ratio). This behaviour is
    attributed to an increase of the amount of simple organic compounds
    resulting from enzymatic activity and also to the activity of
    microphytophagous microarthropods. (C) 1999 Elsevier Science Ltd. All
    rights reserved.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    reserved rights Science Elsevier activity also enzymatic from resulting compounds organic simple amount increase attributed behaviour This biomass specific with relationship inverse decreased subsequently complex sources carbon when spring highest estimated communities microbial Diversity summer maximum community living whole work upon based strategy biotic unfavourable climate edaphic winter prevailing degradation litter strategies showed soils accordance varied activities urease phosphatase content descriptors biochemical particular site differences significant variables these Most tracers alkaline respiration soil index diversity abundance richness groups faunal abundances were measured Properties Jura Swiss cycle vegetation during times three been have biological their pertaining grasslands characteristics Several biodiversity mountains grassland cycling matter Organic Matthey Willy Daniel Maire Nicolas Biochemistry Biology Soil
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-98">
  <rdfs:label>
    Saikh et al., Plant and Soil, 1998.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Changes in carbon, nitrogen, and phopshorus levels
    due to deforestation and cultivation: A case study in Simlipal National
    Park, India
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Saikh, H., Varadachari, C., and Ghosh,
    K.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Changes in carbon, nitrogen, and phopshorus levels
    due to deforestation and cultivation: A case study in Simlipal National
    Park, India
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1998
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Plant and Soil
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      137 -
      145
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The study area, within the Simlipal National Park,
    India, provides a rare variety of soil sampling sites. These include
    virgin forests in the proximity of several cultivated areas (where no
    chemical fertilizers or any modern technology has been used and where
    periods of cultivation vary from 5 to a little over 100 yr); samples from
    evergreen forests, deciduous forests and natural grasslands could also be
    obtained. The availability of numerous such samples made it possible to
    use statistical methods to evaluate the changes. This study showed that
    deforestation and cultivation result in statistically significant (P-0.05)
    reduction in organic C, total N and C:N ratios but no significant changes
    in total and available P levels; C:P and N:P ratios are also reduced. Loss
    of organic C and N occurs rapidly in the first 15 yr of cultivation and
    reaches quasi-steady state values around 1-2% organic C and 0.1-0.2% total
    N; extent of reduction is not related to initial levels. Significant
    reduction in C:N, C:P ratios following cultivation suggest that
    mineralisation losses of C are higher than loss of N whereas loss of P is
    lowest. Lack of significant correlation between organic C and P levels in
    all types of soils, suggests that the bulk of the P is in the inorganic
    form. Highest levels of organic C and N were observed in evergreen forests
    followed by deciduous forests, grasslands and cultivated areas in that
    order; total and available P levels, however, showed no significant
    differences. Evergreen vegetative cover appears to provide the ideal
    environment for organic matter accumulation.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    accumulation matter organic environment ideal provide appears cover vegetative Evergreen differences significant showed however levels available total order that areas cultivated grasslands forests deciduous followed evergreen observed were Highest form inorganic bulk suggests soils types between correlation Lack lowest loss whereas than higher losses mineralisation suggest cultivation following ratios reduction Significant initial related extent around values state reaches first rapidly occurs Loss reduced also changes statistically result deforestation study This evaluate methods statistical possible made samples such numerous availability obtained could natural from over little vary periods where used been technology modern fertilizers chemical several proximity virgin include These sites sampling soil variety rare provides India Park National within area case nitrogen carbon Changes Ghosh Soil Plant
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-99">
  <rdfs:label>
    Relch et al., Nature, 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Plant diversity enhances ecosystem resposes to
    elevated CO2 and nitrogen deposition.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Relch, P.B., Knops, J., Tilman, D., Craine, J.,
    Ellsworth, D., Tjoelker, M., Lee, T., Wedin, D., Naeem, S., Bahauddin, D.,
    Hendrey, G., Jose, S., Wrage, K., Goth, J., and Bengston,
    W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Plant diversity enhances ecosystem resposes to
    elevated CO2 and nitrogen deposition.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      809-812
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    deposition nitrogen elevated ecosystem enhances diversity Plant Bengston Goth Jose Wedin Ellsworth Craine Tilman
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-100">
  <rdfs:label>
    Davies et al., Journal of Applied Ecology, 1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Successional responses of a tropical forest termite
    assemblage to experimental habitat perterbation
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Davies, R., Eggleton, P., Dibog, L., Lawton,
    J.H., Bignell, D., Brauman, A., Hartmann, C., Nunes, L., Holt, J.,
    Rouland, C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Successional responses of a tropical forest termite
    assemblage to experimental habitat perterbation
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Applied
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      36
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      946-962
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    1. Research into the successional responses of
    tropical forest communities following disturbance has potential
    applications for habitat restoration. Currently little is known of how
    these responses relate to the recovery of biodiversity and ecosystem
    processes. Succession of assemblages of decomposer arthropods is essential
    for the recovery of the soil community and nutrient cycling processes. 2.
    This study investigated the successional response of a termite assemblage
    to the experimental perturbation of forest habitat in southern Cameroon,
    examining the implications for tropical forest restoration. A randomized
    block design consisting of four experimental perturbations of differing
    severity was established in an old secondary forest in the Mbalmayo Forest
    Reserve. Isolated control sites were left in undisturbed forest. Recovery
    of the termite assemblage was assessed by measuring termite species
    richness and abundance at regular intervals over the subsequent 12 months.
    3. The speed of recovery of the termite assemblage varied with the type
    and extent of perturbation. In treatments involving severe soil and canopy
    disturbance, termite species richness and abundance recovered more rapidly
    when dead wood was left on the ground following perturbation. The
    availability of dead wood also resulted in recolonization by a subset of
    the termite assemblage that was distinct compositionally from that sampled
    from all other treatments. This subset at sites with additional dead wood
    included not only certain wood-feeding species, but also soil feeders. 4.
    The positive effects upon the termite assemblage of leaving substantial
    dead wood on the ground has implications for the restoration of tropical
    forests following human-induced disturbances such as logging. The
    accelerated recovery of termite diversity and assemblage composition is a
    significant component of soil community recovery and the restoration of
    nutrient cycles. These benefits are expected to influence soil fertility
    and, ultimately, forest regeneration. The duration and persistence of
    these effects will depend crucially on the type, scale and intensity of
    the original disturbance. The impact of termites on soil properties, and
    vice versa, clearly deserves more attention in studies of tropical forest
    regeneration and recovery.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    recovery regeneration forest tropical studies attention more deserves clearly versa vice properties soil termites impact disturbance original intensity scale type crucially depend will effects these persistence duration ultimately fertility influence expected benefits These cycles nutrient restoration community component significant composition assemblage diversity termite accelerated logging such disturbances following forests implications ground wood dead substantial leaving upon positive feeders also species certain only included additional with sites subset This treatments other from sampled that compositionally distinct recolonization resulted availability perturbation left when rapidly recovered abundance richness canopy severe involving extent varied speed months subsequent over intervals regular measuring assessed Recovery undisturbed were control Isolated Reserve Forest secondary established severity differing perturbations experimental four consisting design block randomized examining Cameroon southern habitat response successional investigated study processes cycling essential arthropods decomposer assemblages Succession ecosystem biodiversity relate responses known little Currently applications potential communities into Research Successional Nunes Hartmann Brauman Bignell Lawton Eggleton Davies Ecology Applied Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-101">
  <rdfs:label>
    Emmer et al., Biodiversity and Conservation, 1998.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Reversing borealization as a means to restore
    biodiversity in Central-European mountain forests - an example from the
    Krkonose Mountains, Czech Republic
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Emmer, Igino M.; Fanta, Josef; Kobus, Anita Th.;
    Kooijman, Annemieke; Sevink, Jan
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Reversing borealization as a means to restore
    biodiversity in Central-European mountain forests - an example from the
    Krkonose Mountains, Czech Republic
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1998
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Biodiversity and
      Conservation
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      7
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      229-247
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Forestry in the Central-European mountains is
    confronted with a severe forest decline, which is attributed to the
    combined effects of 'borealization', brought about by large scale
    continued spruce (mainly Picea abies) monocultures, and atmospheric
    deposition. Borealization is defined as enhanced soil acidification and
    litter accumulation, retarded nutrient cycling and changed forest climate
    in such planted coniferous forest ecosystems. An additional effect of
    borealization is a major decline in biodiversity of the stands. Based on a
    comparative study of Norway spruce and European beech stands in the
    Krkonose National Park (Czech Republic), it is concluded that traditional
    management should be abandoned and that management should instead focus on
    regeneration towards broadleaved or mixed forest stands, to enhance the
    stability of forest ecosystems and their biodiversity, and to reverse
    borealization in lower montane zones. Available surveys of forest typology
    were evaluated for their suitability in regeneration management and were
    found to be unsuitable, since they reflect the effects of borealization
    rather than true site conditions. The two main pioneer tree species, birch
    (Betula pendula) and mountain ash (Sorbus aucuparia), were found to
    improve soil conditions and reverse borealization. Furthermore, trends in
    natural vegetation and soil development in declined forests and
    clear-cuts, and their relevance for forest restoration management were
    studied, focusing on borealization and plant species diversity. It is
    concluded that this natural development offers very good possibilities for
    a more passive, low-cost restoration management.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    management restoration cost passive more possibilities good very offers development natural this that concluded diversity species plant focusing studied were forest relevance their forests declined soil vegetation trends Furthermore reverse conditions improve found mountain birch tree pioneer main site true than rather effects reflect they since unsuitable regeneration suitability evaluated typology surveys Available zones montane lower biodiversity ecosystems stability enhance stands mixed towards focus instead should abandoned traditional Park National beech European spruce Norway study comparative Based decline major effect additional coniferous planted such climate changed cycling nutrient retarded accumulation litter acidification enhanced defined deposition atmospheric continued scale large about brought combined attributed which severe with confronted mountains Forestry Republic Czech Mountains from example restore means Reversing Anita Kobus Josef Emmer Conservation Biodiversity
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-102">
  <rdfs:label>
    Janisch et al., Tree Physiology, 2002.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Successional changes in live and dead wood carbon
    stores: implications for net ecosystem
    productivity.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Janisch, J.E., Harmon,
    M.E.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Successional changes in live and dead wood carbon
    stores: implications for net ecosystem productivity.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2002
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Tree Physiology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      22
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      77-89
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    If forests are to be used in CO2 mitigation
    projects, it is essential to understand and quantify the impacts of
    disturbance on net ecosystem productivity (NEP; i.e., the change in
    ecosystem carbon (C) storage with time). We examined the influence of live
    tree and coarse woody debris (CWD) on NEP during secondary succession
    based on data collected along a 500-year chronosequence on the Wind River
    Ranger District, Washington. We developed a simple statistical model of
    live and dead wood accumulation and decomposition to predict changes in
    the woody component of NEP, which we call NEPw. The transition from
    negative to positive NEPw, for a series of scenarios in which none to all
    wood was left after disturbance, occurred between 0 and 57 years after
    disturbance. The timing of this transition decreased as live-tree growth
    rates increased, and increased as CWD left after disturbance increased.
    Maximum and minimum NEPw for all scenarios were 3.9 and -14.1 Mg C ha(-1)
    year(-1), respectively. Maximum live and total wood C stores of 319 and
    393 Mg C ha(-1), respectively, were reached approximately 200 years after
    disturbance. Decomposition rates (k) of CWD ranged between 0.013 and 0.043
    year(-1) for individual stands. Regenerating stands took 41 years to
    attain a mean live wood mass equivalent to the mean mass of CWD left
    behind after logging, 40 years to equal the mean CWD mass in 500-year-old
    forest, and more than 150 years to equal the mean total live and dead wood
    in an old-growth stand. At a rotation age of 80 years, regenerating stands
    stored approximately half the wood C of the remaining nearby old-growth
    forests (predominant age 500 years), indicating that conversion of
    old-growth forests to younger managed forests results in a significant net
    release of C to the atmosphere.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    stand wood dead live total mean equal years than more forest mass logging after behind equivalent attain took stands Regenerating individual between ranged rates Decomposition disturbance approximately reached were respectively stores Maximum scenarios minimum increased left growth decreased transition this timing occurred none which series positive negative from call component woody changes predict decomposition accumulation model statistical simple developed Washington District Ranger River along collected data based succession secondary during debris coarse tree influence examined time with storage carbon ecosystem change productivity impacts quantify understand essential projects mitigation used forests implications Successional Harmon Janisch Physiology Tree
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-105">
  <rdfs:label>
    et al., Journal of ecology, 1987.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen in two contrasting antartic bryophyte
    communities
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    P. Christie
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen in two contrasting antartic bryophyte
    communities
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1987
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of
      ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      75
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      73-93
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    communities bryophyte contrasting Nitrogen Christie ecology Journal two
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-106">
  <rdfs:label>
    Carey et al., Global Change Biology, 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Are old forests underestimated as global carbon
    sinks?
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Carey, Eileen V.; Sala, Anna; Keane, Robert;
    Callaway, Ragan M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Are old forests underestimated as global carbon
    sinks?
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Global Change
      Biology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      7
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      339-344
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Old forests are important carbon pools, but are
    thought to be insignificant as current atmospheric carbon sinks. This
    perception is based on the assumption that changes in productivity with
    age in complex, multiaged, multispecies natural forests can be modelled
    simply as scaled-up versions of individual trees or even-aged stands. This
    assumption was tested by measuring the net primary productivity (NPP) of
    natural subalpine forests in the Northern Rocky Mountains, where NPP is
    from 50% to 100% higher than predicted by a model of an even-age forest
    composed of a single species. If process-based terrestrial carbon models
    underestimate NPP by 50% in just one quarter of the temperate coniferous
    forests throughout the world, then global NPP is being underestimated by
    145 Tg of carbon annually. This is equivalent to 4.3-7.6% of the missing
    atmospheric carbon sink. These results emphasize the need to account for
    multiple-aged, species-diverse, mature forests in models of terrestrial
    carbon dynamics to approximate the global carbon budget.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    budget carbon global approximate dynamics terrestrial models forests mature account need emphasize results These sink atmospheric missing equivalent This annually underestimated being then world throughout coniferous temperate quarter just underestimate species single composed forest model predicted than higher from where Mountains Rocky Northern subalpine natural productivity primary measuring tested assumption stands trees individual versions simply modelled complex with changes that based perception sinks current insignificant thought pools important sinks? Ragan Callaway Robert Keane Anna Sala Eileen Carey Biology Change Global
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-107">
  <rdfs:label>
    Neill et al., Soil Biology and Biochemistry, 1995.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen dynamics in soils of forests and active
    pastures in the western brazilian amazon basin
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Neill, Christopher; Piccolo, Marisa C.;
    Steudler, Paul A.; Melillo, Jerry M.; Feigl, Brigitte J.; Cerri, Carlos
    C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen dynamics in soils of forests and active
    pastures in the western brazilian amazon basin
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1995
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Biology and
      Biochemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      27
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1167-1175
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    To investigate the influence of forest conversion
    to pasture on soil N transformations, we compared soil inorganic-N pools
    and net mineralization and nitrification rates along two chronosequences
    of upland (terra firme) forest and pastures ranging in age from 4 to 82
    years in the state of Rondonia in the western Brazilian Amazon Basin.
    Forest and pasture soils had similar total extractable inorganic-N pools
    at 0-5 and 5-10 cm depths. Ammonium-N and NO3--N pools were of similar
    magnitude in forest soils (2-10 mu g N g(-1) dry soil), while NH4+-N
    dominated pasture soil inorganic-N pools. Annual average net N
    mineralization rates for the two chronosequences at 0-5 cm depth in the
    forests were 1.31-1.88 mu g N g(-1) d.s. d(-1) and exceeded the annual
    average net N mineralization rates measured in pastures of -0.11-0.02 mu g
    N g(-1) d.s. d(-1). Annual average net nitrification rates at 0-5 cm depth
    in forest(1.09-1.46 mu g N g(-1) d.s. d(-1)) were also higher than in
    pastures (0.24-0.25 mu g N g(-1) d.s. d(-1)). Pasture soils had lower net
    N mineralization and net nitrification rates than forest soils even though
    they had approximately equal or higher total C and total N content.
    Pasture age did not affect NH4+-N pools or net nitrification rates, but
    decreased NO3--N pools and net N mineralization rates. Net N
    mineralization rate was unaffected by soil moisture, but net nitrification
    rate decreased at higher soil moisture. Higher net mineralization and
    nitrification rates in forest soils suggest a higher potential for NO3--N
    losses either through leaching or gaseous emissions from intact forests
    compared with established pastures.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    pastures established with compared forests intact from emissions gaseous leaching through either losses potential higher suggest soils forest rates nitrification mineralization Higher moisture soil decreased rate unaffected pools affect Pasture content total equal approximately they though even than lower also were depth average Annual measured annual exceeded pasture dominated while magnitude similar depths extractable Forest Basin Amazon Brazilian western ranging upland along transformations conversion influence investigate basin amazon brazilian active dynamics Nitrogen Carlos Cerri Brigitte Jerry Melillo Paul Marisa Piccolo Christopher Neill Biochemistry Biology Soil
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-108">
  <rdfs:label>
    Uhl et al., Ecology, 1984.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Succession and nutrient dynamics following forest
    cutting and burning in Amazonia
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Uhl, Christopher; Jordan, Carl
    F.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Succession and nutrient dynamics following forest
    cutting and burning in Amazonia
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1984
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      65
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1476-1490
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Amazonia burning cutting forest following dynamics nutrient Succession Carl Jordan Christopher Ecology and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-109">
  <rdfs:label>
    Keller et al., Geophys Res Lett, 1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Production of nitrous oxide and consumption of
    methane by forest soils.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Keller, M., T.j. Goreau, S.C. Wofsy, W.A.
    kaplan, and M.B. McElroy
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Production of nitrous oxide and consumption of
    methane by forest soils.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Geophys Res Lett
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      10
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1156-1159
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils forest methane consumption oxide nitrous Production kaplan Keller Lett
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-110">
  <rdfs:label>
    Goreau et al., to be published in Proceedings: Workshop on
    biogeochemistry of tropical rainforst: Problems for research.,
    1985.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Effects of deforestation on sources and sinks of
    atmospheric carbon dioxide, nitrous oxide and methane from some Amazonian
    biota and soils
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Goreau, T.J., and W.Z.
    DeMello
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Effects of deforestation on sources and sinks of
    atmospheric carbon dioxide, nitrous oxide and methane from some Amazonian
    biota and soils
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1985
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      to be published in Proceedings: Workshop on
      biogeochemistry of tropical rainforst: Problems for
      research.
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils biota some from methane oxide nitrous dioxide carbon atmospheric sinks sources deforestation Effects research Problems tropical biogeochemistry Workshop Proceedings published and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-111">
  <rdfs:label>
    Mosier et al., Soil Science Society American Journal,
    1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrous oxide emissions from a native shortgrass
    prairie
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Mosier, A.R., M. Stillwell, W.J. Parton, and
    R.G. Woodman
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrous oxide emissions from a native shortgrass
    prairie
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Science Society American
      Journal
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      45
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      617-619
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    prairie native from emissions oxide Nitrous Woodman Parton Stillwell Mosier Journal American Society Science Soil
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-112">
  <rdfs:label>
    Smith et al., Geochim Cosmo chim Acta, 1983.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrous oxide emission from Gulf Coast
    wetlands
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Smith, C.J., R.D. DeLaune, and W.h. Patrick Jr.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrous oxide emission from Gulf Coast
    wetlands
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1983
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Geochim Cosmo chim
      Acta
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      47
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1805-1814
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    wetlands Coast Gulf from emission oxide Nitrous Patrick Smith Acta chim Cosmo
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-113">
  <rdfs:label>
    Duxbury et al., Nature, 1982.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Emissions of nitrous oxide from
    soils
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Duxbury, J.M., D.R. Bouldin, R.E. Terry, and
    R.L. Tate III
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Emissions of nitrous oxide from
    soils
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1982
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      462-464
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils from oxide nitrous Emissions Tate Terry Bouldin Duxbury Nature III
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-114">
  <rdfs:label>
    Bremer et al., Geophys Res Lett, 1980.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Seasonal variability in emission of nitrous oxide
    from soil
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Bremer, J.M., S.G. Robbins, and A.M.
    Blackmer
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Seasonal variability in emission of nitrous oxide
    from soil
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1980
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Geophys Res Lett
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      7
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      641-644
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soil from oxide nitrous emission variability Seasonal Blackmer Robbins Bremer Lett
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-115">
  <rdfs:label>
    Breitenbeck et al., Geophys Res Lett, 1980.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Effects of differetn nitrogen fertilizers on
    emission of nitrous oxide from soil
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Breitenbeck, G.A., A.M. Blackmer, and J.M.
    Bremner
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Effects of differetn nitrogen fertilizers on emission
    of nitrous oxide from soil
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1980
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Geophys Res Lett
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      7
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      85-88
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soil from oxide nitrous emission fertilizers nitrogen Effects Bremner Blackmer Lett
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-116">
  <rdfs:label>
    Hutchinson et al., Soil Science Society of America Journal,
    1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Improved soil cover method for field measurement of
    nitrous oxide fluxes
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Hutchinson, G.L., and A.R.
    Mosier
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Improved soil cover method for field measurement of
    nitrous oxide fluxes
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Science Society of America
      Journal
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      45
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      311-316
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    fluxes oxide nitrous measurement field method cover soil Improved Mosier Hutchinson Journal America Society Science Soil for
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-117">
  <rdfs:label>
    McKenny et al., Gephys Res Lett, 1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Rates of N20 evolution from N fertilized
    soil
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    McKenny, D.J., D.L. Wade, and W.I.
    Findlay
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Rates of N20 evolution from N fertilized
    soil
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Gephys Res Lett
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      5
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      777-780
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soil fertilized from evolution Rates Findlay Wade Lett
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-118">
  <rdfs:label>
    Ryden, Nature, 1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    N20 exchange between grassland and the
    atmosphere
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Ryden, J.C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    N20 exchange between grassland and the
    atmosphere
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      235-237
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    atmosphere grassland between exchange Ryden Nature and the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-119">
  <rdfs:label>
    Terry et al., Journal of Air Pollution Control Association,
    1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrous oxide emissions from drained, cultivated
    organic soils of South Florida
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Terry, R.E., R.L. Tate, and J.M.
    Duxbury
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrous oxide emissions from drained, cultivated
    organic soils of South Florida
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Air Pollution Control
      Association
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      31
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1173-1176
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Florida South soils organic cultivated drained from emissions oxide Nitrous Duxbury Tate Terry Association Control Pollution Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-120">
  <rdfs:label>
    Freney et al., Nature, 1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Soil as a source of sink for atmospheric nitrous
    oxide
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Freney, J.R., D.T. Denmead, and J.R.
    Simpson
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Soil as a source of sink for atmospheric nitrous
    oxide
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      530-532
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    oxide nitrous atmospheric sink source Soil Simpson for
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-121">
  <rdfs:label>
    Slemr et al., Journal of Atmospheric chemistry, 1984.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrous oxide emissions from fertilized and
    unfertilized soils in a subtropical region
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Slemr, F., R. Conrad, and W.
    Seiler
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrous oxide emissions from fertilized and
    unfertilized soils in a subtropical region
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1984
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Atmospheric
      chemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      1
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      159-169
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    region subtropical soils unfertilized fertilized from emissions oxide Nitrous Seiler Conrad chemistry Atmospheric Journal and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-122">
  <rdfs:label>
    Conrad et al., Journal of Geophysical Res, 1984.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Factors influencing the loss of fertilizer nitrogen
    in the atmosphere as N20
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Conrad, R., W. Seiler, and G.
    Bunse
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Factors influencing the loss of fertilizer nitrogen
    in the atmosphere as N20
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1984
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Geophysical
      Res
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      88
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      6709-6718
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    atmosphere nitrogen fertilizer loss influencing Factors Seiler Conrad Geophysical Journal the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-123">
  <rdfs:label>
    Seiler et al., Journal of Air Pollution Control Association,
    1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Field measurements of natural and
    fertilized-induced N20 release rates from soils
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Seiler, W. an dr.
    Conrad
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Field measurements of natural and fertilized-induced
    N20 release rates from soils
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Air Pollution Control
      Association
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      31
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      767-772
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils from rates release natural measurements Field Conrad Seiler Association Control Pollution Journal and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-124">
  <rdfs:label>
    Keller et al., Journal of Geophysical Research, 1986.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Emissions of N20, CH4, and CO2 from tropical forest
    soils
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Keller, M., Kaplan, W.A., and Wofsy,
    S.C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Emissions of N20, CH4, and CO2 from tropical forest
    soils
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1986
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Geophysical
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      91
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      791-802
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils forest tropical from Emissions Kaplan Keller Research Geophysical Journal and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-125">
  <rdfs:label>
    Krause, Canadian Journal of Forest Research, 1982.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrate formation and movement before and after
    clear-cutting of a monitored watershet in central New Brunswick,
    Canada
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Krause, H.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrate formation and movement before and after
    clear-cutting of a monitored watershet in central New Brunswick,
    Canada
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1982
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Canadian Journal of Forest
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      12
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      922-930
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Canada Brunswick central monitored after before movement formation Nitrate Krause Research Forest Journal Canadian and New
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-126">
  <rdfs:label>
    Livingston et al., Journal of Geophysical Research,
    1988.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrous oxide flux and nitrogen transformations
    across a landscape gradient in Amazonia
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Livingston, G.P., Vitousek, P.M., Matson,
    P.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrous oxide flux and nitrogen transformations
    across a landscape gradient in Amazonia
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1988
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Geophysical
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      93
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1593-1599
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Amazonia gradient landscape across transformations nitrogen flux oxide Nitrous Matson Livingston Research Geophysical Journal and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-127">
  <rdfs:label>
    Reich et al., Nature, 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Plant diversity enhances ecosystem responses to
    elevated CO2 and nitrogen deposition
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Reich, P.B., Knops, J., Tilman, D., Craine, J.,
    Ellsworth,D., Tjoelker, M., Lee, T., Wedin, D., Naeem, S., Bahauddin, D.,
    Hendrey, G., Jose, S., Wrage, K., Goth, J., and Bengston,
    W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Plant diversity enhances ecosystem responses to
    elevated CO2 and nitrogen deposition
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      809-812
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Human actions are causing declines in plant
    biodiversity, increases in atmospheric CO2 concentrations and increases in
    nitrogen deposition; however, the interactive effects of these factors on
    ecosystem processes are unknown(1,2). Reduced biodiversity has raised
    numerous concerns, including the possibility that ecosystem functioning
    may be affected negatively(1-4), which might be particularly important in
    the face of other global changes (5,6). Here we present results of a
    grassland field experiment in Minnesota, USA, that tests the hypothesis
    that plant diversity and composition influence the enhancement of biomass
    and carbon acquisition in ecosystems subjected to elevated atmospheric CO2
    concentrations and nitrogen deposition. The study experimentally
    controlled plant diversity (1, 4, 9 or 16 species), soil nitrogen
    (unamended versus deposition of 4 g of nitrogen per m(2) per yr) and
    atmospheric CO2 concentrations using free-air CO2 enrichment (ambient, 368
    mu mol mol(-1), versus elevated, 560 mu mol mol(-1)). We found that the
    enhanced biomass accumulation in response to elevated levels of CO2 or
    nitrogen, or their combination, is less in species-poor than in
    species-rich assemblages.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    assemblages than less combination their nitrogen levels elevated response accumulation biomass enhanced versus enrichment using concentrations atmospheric deposition soil diversity plant controlled experimentally study subjected ecosystems acquisition carbon enhancement influence composition that hypothesis tests Minnesota experiment field grassland results present Here changes global face important particularly might which affected functioning ecosystem possibility including concerns numerous raised biodiversity Reduced processes factors these effects interactive however increases declines causing actions Human responses enhances Plant Bengston Goth Jose Wedin Ellsworth Craine Tilman Reich Nature
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-128">
  <rdfs:label>
    Niklaus et al., Oecologia, 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    A link between plant diversity, elevated CO2, and
    soil nitrate
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Niklaus, P.A., Kandeler, E., Leadley, P.W.,
    Schmid, B., Tsherko, D., Korner, C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    A link between plant diversity, elevated CO2, and
    soil nitrate
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Oecologia
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      540-548
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Interactive effects of reductions in plant species
    diversity and increases in atmospheric CO2 were investigated in a
    long-term study in nutrient-poor calcareous grassland. Throughout the
    experiment, soil nitrate was persistently increased at low plant species
    diversity, and CO2 enrichment reduced soil [NO3-] at all levels of plant
    species diversity. In our study, soil [NO3-] was unrelated to root length
    density, microbial biomass N, community legume contents, and experimental
    plant communities differed only little in total N pools. However,
    potential nitrification revealed exactly the same treatment effects as
    soil [NO3-], providing circumstantial evidence that nitrification rates
    drove the observed changes in [NO3-]. One possible explanation for plant
    diversity effects on nitrification lies in spatial and temporal
    interspecific differences in plant N uptake, which would more often allow
    accumulation of NH4+ in part of the soil profile at low diversity than in
    more species-rich plant communities. Consequently, nitrification rates and
    soil [NO3-] would increase. Elevated CO2 increased soil water contents,
    which may have improved NO3- diffusion to the root surface thereby
    reducing soil [NO3-]. Higher soil moisture at elevated CO2 might also
    reduce nitrification rates due to less aerobic conditions. The accordance
    of the diversity effect on soil [NO3-] with previous experiments suggests
    that increased soil [NO3-] at low species diversity is a fairly general
    phenomenon, although the mechanisms causing high [NO3-] may vary. In
    contrast, experimental evidence for effects of CO2 enrichment on soil
    [NO3-] is ambiguous, and the antagonistic interaction of plant species
    reductions and elevated CO2 we have observed is thus probably less
    universal.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    universal less probably thus observed have elevated reductions species plant interaction antagonistic ambiguous soil enrichment effects evidence experimental contrast vary high causing mechanisms although phenomenon general fairly diversity increased that suggests experiments previous with effect accordance conditions aerobic rates nitrification reduce also might moisture Higher reducing thereby surface root diffusion improved which contents water Elevated increase would Consequently communities more than profile part accumulation allow often uptake differences interspecific temporal spatial lies explanation possible changes drove circumstantial providing treatment same exactly revealed potential However pools total little only differed legume community biomass microbial density length unrelated study levels reduced persistently nitrate experiment Throughout grassland calcareous term long investigated were atmospheric increases Interactive between link Korner Schmid Leadley
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-129">
  <rdfs:label>
    Vitousek et al., Forest sci., 1979.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrate losses from Disturbed
    Forests
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Vitousek, Peter M. Melillo, Jerry
    M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrate losses from Disturbed
    Forests
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1979
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Forest sci.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      25
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      605-619
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Forests Disturbed from losses Nitrate Jerry Melillo Peter Forest
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-130">
  <rdfs:label>
    Matson et al., Ecology, 1987.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen transformations following tropical forest
    felling and burning on a volcanic soil
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Matson, Pamela; Vitousek, Peter M.; Ewel, John
    J.; Mazzarino, Maria Julia; Robertson, G.
    Philip
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen transformations following tropical forest
    felling and burning on a volcanic soil
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1987
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      68
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      491-502
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soil volcanic burning felling forest tropical following transformations Nitrogen Philip Robertson Julia Maria Mazzarino John Peter Pamela Matson Ecology and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-131">
  <rdfs:label>
    Smith, Science, 1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Marine macrophytes as a global carbon
    sink.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Smith, S.V.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Marine macrophytes as a global carbon
    sink.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Science
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      838-840
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    sink carbon global Marine Smith Science
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-132">
  <rdfs:label>
    Goulden et al., Science, 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Exchange of carbon dioxide by a deciduous forest:
    response to interannual climate variability.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Goulden, M.L, Munger, J.W, Fan, S.M., Daube,
    B.C., Wofsy, S.C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Exchange of carbon dioxide by a deciduous forest:
    response to interannual climate variability.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Science
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1576-1578
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The annual net uptake of CO2 by a deciduous forest
    in New England varied from 1.4 to 2.8 metric tons of carbon per hectare
    between 1991 and 1995. Carbon sequestration was higher than average in
    1991 because of increased photosynthesis and in 1995 because of decreased
    respiration. Interannual shifts in photosynthesis were associated with the
    timing of leaf expansion and senescence. Shifts in annual respiration were
    associated with anomalies in soil temperature, deep snow in winter, and
    drought in summer. If this ecosystem is typical of northern biomes,
    interannual climate variations on seasonal time scales may modify annual
    CO2 exchange in the Northern Hemisphere by 1 gigaton of carbon or more
    each year.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    year each more carbon Hemisphere Northern exchange annual modify scales time seasonal variations climate northern typical ecosystem this summer drought winter snow deep temperature soil anomalies with associated were respiration Shifts senescence expansion leaf timing photosynthesis shifts decreased because increased average than higher sequestration Carbon between hectare tons metric from varied England forest deciduous uptake variability response dioxide Exchange Daube Munger Goulden Science
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-133">
  <rdfs:label>
    Barr et al., Canadian Journal of Forest Research,
    2002.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Comparing the carbon budgets of boreal and
    temperate deciduous forest stands.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Barr, A.G., Griffis, T.J., Black, T.A., Lee, L,
    Staebler, R.M., Fuentes, J.D., Chen, Z., Morganstern,
    K.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Comparing the carbon budgets of boreal and temperate
    deciduous forest stands.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2002
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Canadian Journal of Forest
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      32
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      813-822
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Boreal and temperate deciduous forests at northern
    mid-latitudes play an important role in the global carbon cycle. We
    analyze 3 years (1996-1998) of eddy-covariance carbon dioxide flux
    measurements from two contrasting deciduous forest ecosystems in the
    boreal and temperate regions of central Canada. The two forest stands have
    similar ages, heights, and leaf area indices but differ in species
    composition and climate. Mean annual net ecosystem productivity (NEP) was
    similar for the two ecosystems, varying between 0.7 and 2.7 t Cha(-1)
    (boreal) and 0.6 and 2.4 t Cha(-1) (temperate). In the boreal ecosystem,
    interannual differences in NEP were primarily controlled by early spring
    temperature. The warm spring of 1998 caused early leaf out and increased
    photosynthesis but had little effect on respiration. In the temperate
    ecosystem, the same warm spring not only caused early leaf out but also
    increased respiration and drought stress. The contrasting impact of the
    warm spring on annual NEP at the two sites illustrates the complexity of
    interpreting climatic impacts on the forest carbon balance. It also
    illustrates two competing influences of climate change on NEP: spring
    warming, which promotes photosynthesis and increases NEP, and increased
    soil temperature and drought, which promote respiration and reduce
    photosynthesis, thus reducing NEP. We discuss the need for a consistent
    data post-processing methodology in ecosystem intercomparisons. We also
    compare our results with a recent synthesis of data from European forests.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    forests European from data synthesis recent with results compare also ecosystem methodology consistent need discuss reducing thus photosynthesis reduce respiration promote which drought temperature soil increased increases promotes warming spring change climate influences competing illustrates balance carbon forest impacts climatic interpreting complexity sites annual warm impact contrasting stress leaf early caused only same temperate effect little controlled primarily were differences boreal between varying ecosystems similar productivity Mean composition species differ indices area heights ages have stands Canada central regions deciduous measurements flux dioxide years analyze cycle global role important play northern Boreal budgets Comparing Chen Fuentes Staebler Black Griffis Barr Research Forest Journal Canadian
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-135">
  <rdfs:label>
    et al., Soil Biology and Biochemistry, 1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitorgen mineraliazation and nitrification
    following land conversion in montane Ecuador
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    C.C Rhoades and D.C.
    Coleman
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitorgen mineraliazation and nitrification following
    land conversion in montane Ecuador
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Biology and
      Biochemistry
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      31
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1347-1354
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The lower montane zone of northwestern Ecuador,
    like many parts of the tropics, is undergoing rapid conversion from native
    forest vegetation to crop and pastureland. The current landscape is a
    mosaic of agricultural land, forest fragments and second-growth vegetation
    in various stages of development. While there is abundant research
    documenting the effects of land-use change in the lowland tropics, such
    information is scarce for montane regions on young volcanic soils. We
    compared foxtail pasture (Setaria sphacelata, [(Schumach.) Stapf and C.E.
    Hubb.]) and traditional, mixed-species pasture with undisturbed old-growth
    forest, 15-20 y-old secondary forest and 5-10 y-old shrubby regrowth. At
    two replicates of each vegetation class, we measured soil nitrogen and
    carbon pools, in situ net nitrogen mineralization and nitrification, soil
    respiration and soil physical properties. Setaria pasture decreased soil
    NO3--N pools and net mineralization and nitrification rates compared to
    mature forest, secondary vegetation, and mixed-species pasture. Soil
    NO3--N in Setaria pastures, during wet and dry seasons, was 40 and 25% of
    amounts measured in other vegetation types. Net nitrification rates were
    also lower beneath Setaria during both seasons, the greatest difference
    occurring during the wet season. Net nitrification rates increased
    considerably (two-fold and greater) under wet season conditions beneath
    all vegetation types except Setal ia pasture. Soils beneath both pasture
    types were wetter and had higher bulk density than mature and
    second-growth forests. Conversion to pasture produces widely varying
    effects on soil N dynamics depending on characteristics of the pasture
    species, such as Setaria['s extremely dense root system. Reduced soil N
    availability beneath Setaria pasture will affect both long-term pasture
    productivity and subsequent forest regeneration in abandoned pastures.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    pastures abandoned regeneration forest subsequent productivity pasture term long both affect will beneath availability soil Reduced system root dense extremely such species characteristics depending dynamics effects varying widely produces Conversion forests mature than density bulk higher wetter were types Soils Setal except vegetation conditions season under considerably increased rates nitrification during occurring difference greatest seasons lower also other measured amounts Soil secondary compared mineralization pools decreased properties physical respiration nitrogen situ carbon class each replicates shrubby undisturbed with traditional Stapf foxtail soils volcanic young regions montane scarce information tropics lowland change land documenting research abundant there While development stages various fragments agricultural mosaic landscape current pastureland crop native from conversion rapid undergoing parts many like Ecuador northwestern zone following Coleman Rhoades Biochemistry Biology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-136">
  <rdfs:label>
    McClaugherty et al., Ecology, 1982.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    "The Role of Fine Roots in the Organic Matter and
    Nitrogen Budgets of Two Forested Ecosystems"
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    McClaugherty, Charles A.; Aber, John D.:
    Melillo, Jerry M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    "The Role of Fine Roots in the Organic Matter and
    Nitrogen Budgets of Two Forested Ecosystems"
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1982
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      63
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1481-1490
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Ecosystems Forested Budgets Nitrogen Matter Organic Roots Fine Role Jerry Melillo John Aber Charles The and Two
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-137">
  <rdfs:label>
    Garcia-Moya et al., Ecology, 1970.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Contribution of shrubs to the nitrogen economy of a
    desert-wash plant community.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Garcia-Moya, Edmundo; McKell, Cyrus
    M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Contribution of shrubs to the nitrogen economy of a
    desert-wash plant community.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1970
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      51
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      81-No
      d
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    community plant economy nitrogen shrubs Contribution Cyrus Edmundo
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-138">
  <rdfs:label>
    Comeau et al., 1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    NPP Boreal Forest: Canal Flats, Canada,
    1984
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Comeau, P. G., and J. P.
    Kimmins
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    NPP Boreal Forest: Canal Flats, Canada,
    1984
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:web-page
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Canada Flats Canal Forest Boreal Kimmins Comeau
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-139">
  <rdfs:label>
    Livingston et al., Journal of Geophysical Research,
    1988.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrous oxide flux and nitrogen transformations
    across a landscape gradient in Amazonia
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Livingston, G.P., Vitousek, P.M., and P.A.
    Matson
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrous oxide flux and nitrogen transformations
    across a landscape gradient in Amazonia
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1988
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of Geophysical
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      93
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1593-1599
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Amazonia gradient landscape across transformations nitrogen flux oxide Nitrous Matson Livingston Research Geophysical Journal and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-140">
  <rdfs:label>
    Sims et al., Journal of ecology, 1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    The structure and function of ten western North
    American grasslands
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Sims, P. L., J. S. Singh, and W. K. Lauenroth
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    The structure and function of ten western North
    American grasslands
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Journal of
      ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      66
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      251-285
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    grasslands American North western function structure Lauenroth Singh Sims ecology Journal The and ten
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-141">
  <rdfs:label>
    Forman et al., Ecology, 1975.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Canopy lichens with blue-green algae: a nitrogen
    source in a Columbian rain forest.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Forman, Richard T. T.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Canopy lichens with blue-green algae: a nitrogen
    source in a Columbian rain forest.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1975
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      56
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1176-1184
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    forest rain Columbian source nitrogen algae with lichens Canopy Richard Forman Ecology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-142">
  <rdfs:label>
    Hall et al., , 1992.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Biophysical, morphological, canopy optical
    property, and productivity data from the Superior National Forest, NASA
    Technical Memorandum 104568
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Hall, F.G., K.F. Huemmrich, D.E. Strebel, S.J.
    Goetz, J.E. Nickeson, and K.D. Woods
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Biophysical, morphological, canopy optical property,
    and productivity data from the Superior National Forest, NASA Technical
    Memorandum 104568
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1992
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Memorandum Technical NASA Forest National Superior from data productivity property optical canopy morphological Biophysical Woods Nickeson Goetz Strebel Hall and the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-143">
  <rdfs:label>
    et al., Ecology, 1980.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen fixation and the nitrogen balance in
    Peatland ecosystems
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Waughman G.J. Bellamy
    D.J
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen fixation and the nitrogen balance in
    Peatland ecosystems
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1980
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      61
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1185-1198
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    ecosystems balance nitrogen fixation Nitrogen Bellamy and the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-144">
  <rdfs:label>
    Dodd et al., Perspectives in Grassland Ecology (N.R. French,
    ed.), 1979.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Analysis of the reponse of a grassland ecosystem to
    stress
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Dodd, J. L., and W. K. Lauenroth
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Analysis of the reponse of a grassland ecosystem to
    stress
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1979
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Perspectives in Grassland Ecology (N.R.
      French, ed.)
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      32
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      43-58
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    stress ecosystem grassland reponse Analysis Lauenroth Dodd French Ecology Grassland Perspectives the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-145">
  <rdfs:label>
    Abrams et al., American J. Botany , 1986.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    A ten year record of above-ground biomass in a
    Kansas tallgrass prairie: effects of fire and topographic
    position
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Abrams, M. D., A. K. Knapp, and L. C. Hulbert
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    A ten year record of above-ground biomass in a Kansas
    tallgrass prairie: effects of fire and topographic
    position
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1986
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      American J. Botany
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      73
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1509-1515
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    position topographic fire effects prairie Kansas biomass record year Hulbert Knapp Abrams American ten and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-146">
  <rdfs:label>
    Risser et al., The True Prairie Ecosystem, 1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    US/IBP Synthesis 16
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Risser, P. G., E. C. Birney, H. D. Blocker, S.
    W. May, W. J. Parton, and J. A. Wiens
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    US/IBP Synthesis 16
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      The True Prairie
      Ecosystem
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      557
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Synthesis Wiens Parton Blocker Birney Risser Ecosystem Prairie True
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-147">
  <rdfs:label>
    Johnson et al., Ecological Applications, 1997.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Soil carbon, nutirents, and mycorrhizae during
    conversion of dry tropical forest to grassland
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Johnson, N.C. and D. A.
    Wedin
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Soil carbon, nutirents, and mycorrhizae during
    conversion of dry tropical forest to grassland
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1997
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Applications
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      7
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      171-182
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Wildfires and alien grass invasion threaten dry
    tropical forests throughout Central America. Efforts to preserve and
    restore these forests will require a better understanding of how
    conversion to grassland changes key belowground processes and organisms
    such as soil organic matter, nutrient cycling, and mycorrhizae. We studied
    forest, edge, and grassland soils from five 60-m transects perpendicular
    to abrupt forest-grassland boundaries in Guanacaste Province, Costa Rica.
    Nutrient concentrations, N mineralization dynamics, and mycorrhizal fungal
    communities were compared across vegetation type (forest, edge, and
    grassland). The dynamics of N mineralization were measured in year-long
    laboratory incubations, and the diversity of mycorrhizal fungal
    communities was assessed from populations of soil-borne spores. Soil C, N,
    and K were lower, while many base cations and micronutrients were higher
    in grassland plots than in forest plots. Although differences in the
    quantity of total soil C and N occurred mainly in the forest-to-edge
    transition, differences in the quality of soil organic matter, as
    reflected by soil C:N ratios and mineralization rates, occurred in the
    edge-to-grassland transition. Beta diversity of mycorrhizal spore
    communities (measured by Sorenson's similarity index) was lower in the
    grassland plots than in the forest plots, indicating that grass invasion
    had caused some convergence. However, total spore density and alpha
    diversity of mycorrhizal spore communities (measured by species richness
    and Simpson's diversity index) were not altered by wildfires and grass
    invasion. These results suggest that persistence and regeneration of
    forest plant species in the grasslands may not be constrained to a
    significant degree by the lack of mycorrhizal symbionts. These grasslands
    appear to be sustainable, alternative stable states for these areas.
    Positive feedbacks between the alien grassland vegetation and both fire
    and nutrient cycling maintain and reinforce this alternative state.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    state alternative this reinforce maintain cycling nutrient fire both vegetation grassland alien between feedbacks Positive areas these states stable sustainable appear grasslands lack degree significant constrained species plant forest regeneration persistence that suggest results These invasion grass wildfires altered were diversity richness communities spore alpha density total However convergence some caused indicating plots than lower similarity Beta transition occurred rates mineralization ratios soil reflected matter organic quality differences mainly quantity Although higher micronutrients cations base many while Soil spores populations from assessed fungal laboratory measured dynamics edge type across compared concentrations Nutrient Rica Costa Province boundaries abrupt perpendicular transects five soils studied such organisms processes belowground changes conversion understanding better require will forests restore preserve Efforts America Central throughout tropical threaten Wildfires during carbon Wedin Johnson Applications Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-80">
  <rdfs:label>
    Turner et al., Environmental Management, 1988.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Market and nonmarket values of the Georgia
    landscape
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Turner,M G, Odum,E P, Costanza,R, Springer, T
    M
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Market and nonmarket values of the Georgia
    landscape
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1988
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Environmental
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      12
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      209-217
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    landscape Georgia values Market Springer Costanza Odum Turner Management Environmental and the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-81">
  <rdfs:label>
    Lynne et al., Economic value of the coastal
    zone, 1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic value of the coastal
    zone
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Lynne, Gary D., Conroy, Patricia
    D.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic value of the coastal
    zone
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    zone coastal value Economic Patricia Conroy Gary Lynne the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-82">
  <rdfs:label>
    Bell et al., Application of wetland valuation theory to Florida
    Fisheries, 1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Application of wetland valuation theory to Florida
    Fisheries
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Bell,Frederick W.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Application of wetland valuation theory to Florida
    Fisheries
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Fisheries Florida theory valuation wetland Application Frederick Bell
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-83">
  <rdfs:label>
    et al., Global marine biological biodiversity, 1993.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Marine biological diversity: definition and
    importance
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Unknown
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Marine biological diversity: definition and
    importance
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1993
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Global marine biological
      biodiversity
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      9-36
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:book-section
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    importance definition diversity biological Marine Unknown biodiversity marine Global and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-84">
  <rdfs:label>
    Bockstael et al., Marine resource economics, 1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Measuring the benefits of improvements in water
    quality: the Chesapeake Bay
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Bockstael, N. E., McConnell, K.E., Strand,
    I.E.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Measuring the benefits of improvements in water
    quality: the Chesapeake Bay
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Marine resource
      economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      6
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1-18
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Chesapeake quality water improvements benefits Measuring Strand economics resource Marine the Bay
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-85">
  <rdfs:label>
    Batie et al., Southern Journal of Agricultural Economics,
    1978.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economics values attributable to virginia's coastal
    wetlands as inputs in oyster production
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Batie, Sandra, Wilson,
    James
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economics values attributable to virginia's coastal
    wetlands as inputs in oyster production
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1978
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Southern Journal of Agricultural
      Economics
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      111-118
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    production oyster inputs wetlands coastal virginia's attributable values Economics James Wilson Sandra Batie Agricultural Journal Southern
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-86">
  <rdfs:label>
    Whitehead et al., Coastal Management, 1997.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Economic analysis of an estuarine quality
    improvement program: the Ambemarle-Pamlico System
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Whitehead, John, Hoban, Thomas, Clifford,
    William
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Economic analysis of an estuarine quality improvement
    program: the Ambemarle-Pamlico System
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1997
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Coastal
      Management
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      25
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      43-57
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    As part of the National Estuary Program, the
    extensive 5-year Albemarle-Pamlico Estuarine Study was recently concluded.
    The resultant Comprehensive Conservation and Management Plan was designed
    to maintain the ecological integrity of the estuary through long-term
    planning and management. One of the components of this plan is the
    consideration of human dimensions of the Albemarle-Pamlico system,
    including benefits and costs for present and future generations. This
    article presents an economic efficiency analysis of the proposed
    management plan. Under plausible conditions and reasonable data for
    benefits and costs, it appears that the management plan would be an
    efficient government program if the negative externalities associated with
    economic growth of the Albemarle-Pamlico region are controlled.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    controlled region growth economic with associated externalities negative program government efficient would plan management that appears costs benefits data reasonable conditions plausible Under proposed analysis efficiency presents article This generations future present including system dimensions human consideration this components planning term long through estuary integrity ecological maintain designed Plan Management Conservation Comprehensive resultant concluded recently Study Estuarine extensive Program Estuary National part System improvement quality estuarine Economic William Clifford Thomas Hoban John Whitehead Coastal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-87">
  <rdfs:label>
    et al., a world bank country study, 1989.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Philippines-Environment and Natural Resource
    Mangagement Study
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    The World Bank
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Philippines-Environment and Natural Resource
    Mangagement Study
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1989
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      A World Bank country
      study
    </documentation:series-name>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Study Resource Natural Bank World study country bank world and The
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-88">
  <rdfs:label>
    Sathirathai et al., Contemporary Economic Policy,
    2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Valuing mangrove conservation in Southern
    Thailand
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Sathirathai, Suthawan, Barbier, Edward
    B.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Valuing mangrove conservation in Southern
    Thailand
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Contemporary Economic
      Policy
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      19
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      109-122
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Mangroves are ecologically, important coastal
    wetland systems that ale under severe treat globally: In Thailand, the
    main cause Of mangrove conversion is shrimp farming, which is a major
    source Of export income for the country However local communities benefit
    from many direct and indirect uses of mangrove ecosystems and may have a
    strong incentive to protect these areas, which puts them into direct
    confrontational with shrimp farm operators and, by proxy government
    authorities. The article examines whether or not the full conversion of
    mangroves into commercial shrimp farms is worthwhile once the key
    environmental impacts ape taken into account. The estimated economic value
    of mangrove forests to a local community, is in the range of
    $27,264-$35,921 per hectare. This Estimate includes the value to local
    communities of direct use of wood and other resources collected from the
    mangroves as well as additional eternal benefits in terms of off-Shore
    fishery linkages and coastline protection from shrimp, farms. The results
    indicate that, although shrimp farming creates enormous private benefits,
    it is not so economically viable once the externalities generated bq,
    mangrove destruction and water pollution ale included. There is also an
    incentive for local communities to protect mangroves, which in turn
    implies that the rights of: local people to guard and protect this
    resource should be formally, recognized and enforced by law.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    enforced recognized formally should resource this protect guard people local rights that implies turn which communities incentive also There included pollution water destruction mangrove generated externalities once viable economically benefits private enormous creates farming shrimp although indicate results farms from protection coastline linkages fishery terms eternal additional well collected resources other wood direct value includes Estimate This hectare range community forests economic estimated account into taken impacts environmental worthwhile commercial conversion full whether examines article authorities government proxy operators farm with confrontational them puts areas these strong have ecosystems uses indirect many benefit However country income export source major cause main Thailand globally treat severe under systems wetland coastal important ecologically Southern conservation Valuing Edward Barbier Policy Economic Contemporary
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-148">
  <rdfs:label>
    Rustad et al., Oecologia, 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    A meta-analysis of the response of soil
    respiration, net nitrogen mineralization, and aboveground plant growth to
    experimental ecosystem warming
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Rustad, L.E., Campbell, J.L., Marion, G.M.,
    Norby, R. J., Mitchell, M.J., Hartley, A.E., Cornelissen, J.H.C., and J.
    Gurevitch
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    A meta-analysis of the response of soil respiration,
    net nitrogen mineralization, and aboveground plant growth to experimental
    ecosystem warming
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Oecologia
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      126
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      543-562
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Climate change due to greenhouse gas emissions is
    predicted to raise the mean global temperature by 1.0-3.5 degreesC in the
    next 50-100 years. The direct and indirect effects of this potential
    increase in temperature on terrestrial ecosystems and ecosystem processes
    are likely to be complex and highly varied in time and space. The Global
    Change and Terrestrial Ecosystems core project of the International
    Geosphere-Biosphere Programme has recently launched a Network of Ecosystem
    Warming Studies, the goals of which are to integrate and foster research
    on ecosystem-level effects of rising temperature. In this paper, we use
    meta-analysis to synthesize data on the response of soil respiration, net
    N mineralization, and aboveground plant productivity to experimental
    ecosystem warming at 32 research sites representing four broadly defined
    biomes, including high (latitude or altitude) tundra, low tundra,
    grassland, and forest. Warming methods included electrical heat-resistance
    ground cables, greenhouses, vented and unvented field chambers, overhead
    infrared lamps, and passive nighttime warming. Although results from
    individual sites showed considerable variation in response to warming,
    results from the meta-analysis showed that, across all sites and years,
    2-9 years of experimental warming in the range 0.3-6.0 degreesC
    significantly increased soil respiration rates by 20% (with a 95%
    confidence interval of 18-22%), net N mineralization rates by 46% (with a
    95% confidence interval of 30-64%). and plant productivity by 19% (with a
    95% confidence interval of 15-23%). The response of soil respiration to
    warming was generally larger in forested ecosystems compared to low tundra
    and grassland ecosystems, and the response of plant productivity was
    generally larger in low tundra ecosystems than in forest and grassland
    ecosystems. With the exception of aboveground plant productivity, which
    showed a greater positive response to warming in colder ecosystems, the
    magnitude of the response of these three processes to experimental warming
    was not generally significantly related to the geographic, climatic, or
    environmental variables evaluated in this analysis. This underscores the
    need to understand the relative importance of specific factors (such as
    temperature, moisture, site quality, vegetation type, successional status,
    land-use history, etc.) at different spatial and temporal scales, and
    suggests that we should be cautious in "scaling up" responses from the
    plot and site level to the landscape and biome level. Overall,
    ecosystem-warming experiments are shown to provide valuable insights on
    the response of terrestrial ecosystems to elevated temperature.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    temperature elevated ecosystems terrestrial response insights valuable provide shown experiments Overall level biome landscape site plot from responses scaling cautious should that suggests scales temporal spatial different history land status successional type vegetation quality moisture factors specific importance relative understand need underscores This analysis this evaluated variables environmental climatic geographic related significantly generally warming experimental processes three these magnitude colder positive greater showed which productivity plant aboveground exception With grassland forest than tundra larger compared forested respiration soil interval confidence with rates mineralization increased range years sites across results variation considerable individual Although nighttime passive lamps infrared overhead chambers field unvented vented greenhouses cables ground electrical included methods Warming high including defined broadly four representing research ecosystem data synthesize paper rising effects foster integrate goals Studies Ecosystem Network launched recently Programme International project core Ecosystems Terrestrial Change Global space time varied highly complex likely increase potential indirect direct next global mean raise predicted emissions greenhouse change Climate growth nitrogen Hartley Mitchell Norby Marion Campbell Rustad
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-149">
  <rdfs:label>
    Krause, Can J For Res, 1982.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrate formation and movement before and after
    clear-cutting of a monitored watershed in central New Brunswick,
    Canada
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Krause, H.H.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrate formation and movement before and after
    clear-cutting of a monitored watershed in central New Brunswick,
    Canada
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1982
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Can J For Res
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      12
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      922-930
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Canada Brunswick central watershed monitored after before movement formation Nitrate Krause and New
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-150">
  <rdfs:label>
    Hooper et al., Ecological Monographs, 1998.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Effects of plant compostion and diversity on
    nutrient cycling
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Hooper, D., and P.M.
    Vitousek
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Effects of plant compostion and diversity on nutrient
    cycling
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1998
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Monographs
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      68
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      121-149
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    We evaluated the effects of plant functional group
    richness on seasonal patterns of soil nitrogen and phosphorus cycling,
    using serpentine grassland in south San Jose, California. We established
    experimental plots with four functional types of plants: early-season
    annual forbs (E), late-season annual forbs (L), nitrogen-fixers (N), and
    perennial bunchgrasses (P). These groups differ in several traits relevant
    to nutrient cycling, including phenology, rooting depth, root:shoot ratio,
    size, and leaf C:N content. Two or three species of each group were
    planted in single functional group (SFG) treatments, and in two-, three-,
    and four-way combinations of functional groups. We analyzed available
    nutrient pool sizes, microbial biomass nitrogen and phosphorus, microbial
    nitrogen immobilization, nitrification rates, and leaching losses. We used
    an index of "relative resource use" that incorporates the effects of
    plants on pool sizes of several depletable soil resources: inorganic
    nitrogen in all seasons, available phosphorus in all seasons, and water in
    the summer dry season. We found a significant positive relationship
    between increasing relative resource use (including both plant and
    microbial uptake) and increasing plant diversity. The increase in relative
    resource use results because different functional groups have their
    maximum effect on different resources in different seasons: E's dominate
    reduction of inorganic nitrogen pools in winter; L's have a stronger
    depletion of nitrogen in spring and a dominant reduction of water in
    summer; P's have a stronger nitrogen depletion in summer; N-fixers provide
    additional nitrogen in all seasons and have a significant phosphorus
    depletion in all seasons except fall. Single functional group treatments
    varied greatly in relative resource use; for example, the resource use
    index for the L treatment is as high as in the more diverse treatments. We
    expected a reduction of leaching losses as functional group richness
    increased because of differences in rooting depth and seasonal activity
    among these groups. However, measurements of nitrate in soil water leached
    below the rooting zone indicated that, apart from a strong reduction in
    losses in all vegetated treatments compared to the bare treatment, there
    were no effects of increasing plant diversity. While some single
    functional group treatments differed (P less than or equal to L, N), more
    diverse treatments did not. Early-and late-season annuals, but not
    perennial bunchgrasses, had significant positive effects on microbial
    immobilization of nitrogen in short-term (24 h) N-15 experiments. We
    conclude that: (1) total resource use, across many resource axes and
    including both plant and microbial effects, does increase with increasing
    plant diversity on a yearly timescale due to seasonal complementarity; (2)
    while the presence of vegetation has a large effect on ecosystem nitrogen
    retention, nitrogen leaching losses do not necessarily decrease with
    increasing functional group richness; (3) indirect effects of plants on
    microbial processes such as immobilization can equal or exceed direct
    effects of plant uptake on nutrient retention; and (4) plant composition
    (i.e., the identity of the groups present in treatments) in general
    explains much more about the measured nutrient cycling processes than does
    functional group richness alone (i.e., the number of groups present).
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    experiments term short nitrogen immobilization microbial effects positive significant perennial annuals treatments diverse equal than less differed group functional single some While diversity plant increasing were there treatment bare compared vegetated losses reduction strong from apart that indicated zone rooting below leached water soil nitrate measurements However groups these among activity seasonal depth differences because increased richness leaching expected more high index resource example relative greatly varied Single fall except seasons depletion phosphorus have additional provide summer stronger dominant spring winter pools inorganic dominate different resources effect maximum their results increase both between relationship found season available depletable several sizes pool plants incorporates used rates nitrification biomass nutrient analyzed combinations planted each species three content leaf size ratio shoot root phenology including cycling relevant traits differ These forbs annual types four with plots experimental established California Jose south grassland serpentine using patterns evaluated Effects Hooper Monographs Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-151">
  <rdfs:label>
    Symstad et al., Oikos, 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Diversity loss, recruitment limitation, and
    ecosystem functioning: lessons learned from a removal
    experiment
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Symstad, A.J., and D.
    Tilman
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Diversity loss, recruitment limitation, and ecosystem
    functioning: lessons learned from a removal
    experiment
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Oikos
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      92
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      424-435
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    A five-year removal experiment in which plant
    functional group diversity was manipulated found strong limitation of
    ecosystem functioning caused by the differing abilities of remaining
    functional groups to recruit into space left unoccupied by the plants
    removed. We manipulated functional group diversity and composition by
    removing all possible combinations of zero. one, or two plant functional
    groups (forbs, C-3 graminoids, and C-4 graminoids), as well as randomly
    chosen biomass at levels corresponding to the functional group removals,
    from a prairie grassland community. Although random biomass removal
    treatments showed no significant effect of removing biomass in general on
    ecosystem functions measured (P &gt; 0.05), the loss of particular
    functional groups led to significant differences in above(P&lt;0.001) and
    belowground (P&lt;0.001) biomass, rooting-zone (P=0.001) and leached
    (P=0.01) nitrogen, nitrogen miniralization (P&lt;0.001), and community
    drought resistance (P = 0.002). Many of these differences stemmed from the
    marked difference in the ways remaining functional groups responded to the
    experimental removals. Strong recruitment limitation of C-4 graminoids
    resulted in large areas of open ground, high nutrient leaching. and high
    community drought resistance in plots containing just this functional
    group. In contrast, rhizomatous C-3 graminoids quickly colonized space and
    used soil resources made available by the removal of other groups, leading
    to lower soil nitrate in plots containing C-3 graminoids. These effects of
    recruitment limitation on ecosystem functioning illustrate possible
    effects of diversity loss not captured by synthetic experiments in which
    diversity gradients are created by adding high densities of seeds to bare
    soil.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soil bare seeds densities high adding created gradients diversity which experiments synthetic captured loss effects possible illustrate functioning ecosystem limitation recruitment These containing plots nitrate lower leading groups other removal available made resources used space colonized quickly rhizomatous contrast group functional this just resistance drought community leaching nutrient ground open areas large resulted Strong removals experimental responded remaining ways difference marked from stemmed differences these Many nitrogen leached biomass belowground significant particular measured functions general removing effect showed treatments random Although grassland prairie corresponding levels chosen randomly well zero combinations composition manipulated removed plants unoccupied left into recruit abilities differing caused strong found plant experiment learned lessons Diversity Tilman
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-152">
  <rdfs:label>
    Pollock et al., Ecology, 1998.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Plant species richness in riparian wetlands-a test
    of biodiversity theory
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Pollock, M.M., Naiman, R.J., and T.A.
    Hanley
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Plant species richness in riparian wetlands-a test of
    biodiversity theory
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1998
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      79
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      94-105
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    In this study, flood frequency, productivity, and
    spatial heterogeneity were correlated with plant species richness (SX)
    among wetlands on a coastal island in southeast Alaska. Studies of 16
    sites in or near the Kadashan River basin demonstrated nonlinear, unimodal
    relations between flood frequency and SR, productivity and SR, and linear
    relations between SR and the spatial variation of flood frequencies (SVFF)
    within a site. SVFF is caused by microtopographic variation in elevation.
    A nonlinear regression model relating SR to flood frequency and SVFF
    explained much of the variation in SR between wetland communities. Sites
    with intermediate flood frequencies and high SVFF were species-rich, while
    sites frequently, rarely, or permanently flooded and with low SVFF were
    species-poor. The data suggest that small-scale spatial variation can
    dramatically alter the impact of disturbances. The data also support
    Michael Huston's dynamic-equilibrium model of species diversity, which
    predicts the effects of productivity and disturbance on diversity
    patterns. Species-rich sites had low to intermediate levels of
    productivity and intermediate flood frequencies, and species-poor sites
    had very low or high flood frequencies and low productivity, supporting
    the model's predictions. The model was tested at contrasting spatial
    scales (1000 m(2) and 1 m(2)). At the 1000-m(2)? scale, Huston's model
    predicted 78% of the variation in SR. At the microplot scale,
    relationships between SR and flood frequency were weaker, and the
    dynamic-equilibrium model predicted only 36%; of the variation in SR.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    variation only predicted model weaker were frequency flood between relationships scale Huston's scales spatial contrasting tested predictions model's supporting productivity frequencies high very sites intermediate levels patterns diversity disturbance effects predicts which species Michael support also data disturbances impact alter dramatically that suggest with flooded permanently rarely frequently while Sites communities wetland much explained relating regression nonlinear elevation caused site within relations linear unimodal demonstrated basin River near Studies Alaska southeast island coastal wetlands among richness plant correlated heterogeneity study this theory biodiversity test riparian Plant Hanley Naiman Pollock Ecology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-153">
  <rdfs:label>
    Robertson et al., Soil Sci. Am. J., 1984.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Denitrification and nitrous oxide production in
    successional and old-growth Michigan forests
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Robertson, G.P. and J.M.
    Tiedje
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Denitrification and nitrous oxide production in
    successional and old-growth Michigan forests
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1984
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Soil Sci. Am. J.
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      48
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      383-389
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    forests Michigan successional production oxide nitrous Denitrification Robertson Soil and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-154">
  <rdfs:label>
    Garcia-Mendez et al., Oecologia, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen transformations and nitrous oxide flux in
    a tropical deciduous forest in Mexico
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Garcia-Mendez, Goergina; Maass, J. Manuel;
    Matson, Pamela A.; Vitousek, Peter M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen transformations and nitrous oxide flux in a
    tropical deciduous forest in Mexico
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Oecologia
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      88
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      362-366
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Emissions of nitrous oxide and soil nitrogen pools
    and transformations were measured over an annual cycle in two forests and
    one pasture in tropical deciduous forest near Chamela, Mexico. Nitrous
    oxide flux was moderately high (0.5-2.5 ng cm-2 h-1) during the wet season
    and low (&lt; 0.3 ng cm-2 h-1) during the dry season. Annual emissions of
    nitrogen as nitrous oxide were calculated to be 0.5-0.7 kg ha-1 y-1, with
    no substantial difference between the forests and pasture. Wetting of dry
    soil caused a large but short-lived pulse of N2O flux that accounted for
    &lt; 2% of annual flux. Variation in soil water through the season was the
    primary controlling factor for pool sizes of ammonium and nitrate,
    nitrogen transformations, and N2O flux.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    flux transformations nitrogen nitrate ammonium sizes pool factor controlling primary season through water soil Variation annual accounted that pulse lived short large caused Wetting pasture forests between difference substantial with calculated were oxide nitrous emissions Annual during high moderately Nitrous Mexico near forest deciduous tropical cycle over measured pools Emissions Nitrogen Peter Pamela Matson Manuel Maass
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-155">
  <rdfs:label>
    Langis R et al., Ecological Applications, 1991.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen assessments in a constructed and a natural
    salt marsh of San Diego Bay.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Langis R, Zalejko M, Zedler
    JB
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen assessments in a constructed and a natural
    salt marsh of San Diego Bay.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1991
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Applications
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      1
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      40-51
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Soil nitrogen pools were lower in a 4-yr-old
    constructed salt marsh than in an adjacent natural marsh of San Diego Bay.
    Aboveground biomass and foliar nitrogen content of Spartina foliosa were
    both lower for the constructed marsh. Soil organic carbon, which was
    highly positively correlated with total nitrogen, was also lower in
    theconstructed marsh. Rates of nitrogen fixation were higher for the
    natural marsh in surface soils (1 cm depth) but not in the rhizosphere (10
    cm depth). Experimental additions of organic matter increased rates of
    nitrogen fixation substantially for both the constructed and natural marsh
    soils, with glucose stimulating greater increases than Spartina foliosa
    detritus (roots and rhizomes). In comparison with natural marshes studied
    elsewhere, the San Diego Bay sites have low nitrogen pools and little soil
    organic carbon. Nitrogen mineralization rates (in situ incubations) were
    high in both marshes studied. The low nitrogen pools reflect low tidal
    import and infrequent streamflow influxes and, possibly, high nitrogen
    demands of vegetation stressed by hypersaline soils
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    soils stressed vegetation demands nitrogen high possibly infrequent import tidal reflect pools studied marshes both were situ rates mineralization Nitrogen carbon organic soil little have sites Diego elsewhere natural with comparison detritus than increases greater stimulating glucose marsh constructed substantially fixation increased matter additions Experimental rhizosphere surface higher Rates lower also total correlated positively highly which Soil content foliar biomass Aboveground adjacent salt assessments Applications Ecological The low and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-156">
  <rdfs:label>
    Tilman et al., Nature, 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Productivity and sustainability influenced by
    biodiversity in grassland ecosystems
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Tilman, D., Wedin, D., and J.
    Knops
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Productivity and sustainability influenced by
    biodiversity in grassland ecosystems
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Nature
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      718-720
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    THE functioning and sustainability of ecosystems
    may depend on their biological diversity(1-8). Elton's(9) hypothesis that
    more diverse ecosystems are more stable has received much
    attention(1,3,6,7,10-14), but Darwin's proposal(6,15) that more diverse
    plant communities are more productive, and the related
    conjectures(4,5,16,17) that they have lower nutrient losses and more
    sustainable soils, are less well studied(4-6,8,17,18). Here we use a
    well-replicated field experiment, in which species diversity was directly
    controlled, to show that ecosystem productivity in 147 grassland plots
    increased significantly with plant biodiversity, Moreover, the main
    limiting nutrient, soil mineral nitrogen, was utilized more completely
    when there was a greater diversity of species, leading to lower leaching
    loss of nitrogen from these ecosystems. Similarly, in nearby native
    grassland, plant productivity and soil nitrogen utilization increased with
    increasing plant species richness. This supports the
    diversity-productivity and diversity-sustainability hypotheses. Our
    results demonstrate that the loss of species threatens ecosystem
    functioning and sustainability.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    sustainability functioning ecosystem threatens species loss that demonstrate results hypotheses supports This richness plant increasing with increased utilization nitrogen soil productivity grassland native nearby Similarly ecosystems these from leaching lower leading diversity greater there when completely more utilized mineral nutrient limiting main Moreover biodiversity significantly plots show controlled directly which experiment field Here well less soils sustainable losses have they related productive communities diverse much received stable hypothesis biological their depend influenced Productivity Wedin Tilman Nature
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-157">
  <rdfs:label>
    Maass et al., , 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    NPP Tropical Forest: Chamela, Mexico,
    1982-1995
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Maass, M., and A.
    Martinez-Yrizar
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    NPP Tropical Forest: Chamela, Mexico,
    1982-1995
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Mexico Forest Tropical Maass
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-158">
  <rdfs:label>
    Weaver, , 1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    NPP Tropical Forest: Cinnamon Bay, U.S. Virgin
    Islands
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Weaver, P.L.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    NPP Tropical Forest: Cinnamon Bay, U.S. Virgin
    Islands
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Islands Virgin Cinnamon Forest Tropical Weaver
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-159">
  <rdfs:label>
    Matson et al., , 1990.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Sources of variation in nitrous oxide flux from
    amazonian ecosystems
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Matson, P. A.; Vitousek, P. M.; Livingston, G.
    P.; Swanberg, N. A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Sources of variation in nitrous oxide flux from
    amazonian ecosystems
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      95
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      16,789-16,798
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    ecosystems from flux oxide nitrous variation Sources Swanberg Livingston Matson
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-162">
  <rdfs:label>
    Hook et al., Ecology, 2000.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Biogeochemistry in a shortgrass landscape: Control
    by topography, soil texture, and microclimate
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Hook, P.B. and Burke,
    I.C.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Biogeochemistry in a shortgrass landscape: Control by
    topography, soil texture, and microclimate
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2000
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      81
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      2686-2703
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Biogeochemistry of terrestrial ecosystems is
    controlled by interactions among factors operating at several spatial and
    temporal scales. The purpose of this study was to evaluate the relative
    importance and interaction of relatively static landscape factors and more
    dynamic factors in a shortgrass steppe landscape. The landscape factors
    examined were topographic position, and soil texture. The dynamic factors
    studied were seasonal climate and the localized effects of individual
    plants on soils. Patterns were evaluated by sampling soil between and
    under individual Bouteloua gracilis plants in paired upland (erosional)
    and lowland (depositional) plots at eight locations at the Central Plains
    Experimental Range (CPER), Colorado. We quantified five organic C and N
    pools (total, fine and coarse particulate organic matter [POM],
    mineral-associated organic matter [MAOM], and potentially mineralizable C
    and N), and we estimated seasonal patterns of in situ N dynamics with
    three methods (extractable inorganic N, net N mineralization in uncovered
    cores, and N adsorbed on ion exchange resin [IER] bags). Topographic
    position and soil texture each explained much of the landscape-scale
    variation of C and N pools and vegetation structure. Most lowland plots
    were enriched in silt, clay, C, and N relative to adjacent upland plots,
    and topographic position affected most pools significantly. Most
    vegetation and biogeochemical variables were strongly correlated with soil
    sand content. Across the range of sand content encountered (40-83%), the
    fraction of area in bare soil openings &gt;5 cm across increased
    sevenfold, and most C and N fractions increased by 2-4.5 times.
    Plant-induced, microscale heterogeneity of soil C and N was comparable in
    magnitude to landscape-scale heterogeneity for pools with more rapid
    turnover (POM and mineralizable C and N), but presence or absence of
    plants did not affect more stable, mineral-associated organic matter.
    Plant-induced heterogeneity was significant in all locations, but its
    importance likely decreases with decreasing sand content as cover becomes
    more continuous, particularly in lowlands. Total extractable inorganic N
    and nitrate, N adsorbed on resin bags, and the proportion of mineralized N
    that was nitrified during incubations increased with increasing soil water
    content or precipitation, but net N mineralization did not vary
    systematically with precipitation. Inorganic N availability was greatest
    during relatively moist spring periods, and these were the only times when
    indices of in situ N availability followed the spatial patterns expected
    from laboratory assays of C and N pool distribution. The relatively weak
    spatial patterns for N dynamics contrast with the substantial landscape
    and individual-plant scale variation in C and N pools. Landscape patterns
    of N mineralization and availability may be tied to N pools, such as POM
    N, that are not strongly related to topography or texture. Particulate
    organic matter appears to be especially important to N retention and
    availability on sandy soils, which typify most sites at the CPER; the
    proportion of total N residing in POM was high and POM C:N ratios were low
    in sandy upland soils. We suggest that soil texture is a key proximal
    control over biogeochemical processes and is largely responsible for
    observed landscape-scale patterns, including topographic differences.
    Models that integrate effects of texture and topography have the potential
    to link landscape biogeochemical patterns to short-term processes that
    directly influence SOM dynamics and to long-term geomorphic processes that
    influence soil distribution, including eolian redistribution of soil
    materials, which is important in many dry regions.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    differences topographic including patterns observed responsible largely processes biogeochemical over control proximal texture soil that suggest topography related strongly such pools tied availability mineralization Landscape variation scale landscape substantial with contrast dynamics spatial weak relatively lowlands particularly continuous more becomes cover content sand decreasing decreases likely importance locations significant heterogeneity times increased fractions most sevenfold across openings bare area fraction encountered range Across correlated were variables vegetation Most significantly affected position plots upland adjacent relative clay silt enriched lowland structure much explained each Topographic resin exchange adsorbed cores uncovered inorganic methods three situ seasonal estimated mineralizable potentially matter organic particulate coarse fine five quantified Colorado Range Experimental Plains Central eight paired plants individual under between sampling evaluated Patterns soils effects localized climate studied factors dynamic examined steppe static interaction evaluate study this purpose scales temporal several operating among interactions controlled ecosystems terrestrial Biogeochemistry microclimate Control Burke Hook Ecology
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-163">
  <rdfs:label>
    Wofsy et al., Science, 1993.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Net exchange of CO2 in a mid-latitude
    forest.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Wofsy, S.C., Goulden, M.L., Munger, J.W., Fan,
    S.M., Bakwin, P.S., Daube, B.C., Bassow, S.L., Bazzaz,
    F.A.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Net exchange of CO2 in a mid-latitude
    forest.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1993
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Science
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      127
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1314-1317
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The eddy correlation method was used to measure the
    net ecosystem exchange of carbon dioxide continuously from April 1990 to
    December 1991 in a deciduous forest in central Massachusetts. The annual
    net uptake was 3.7 +/- 0.7 metric tons of carbon per hectare per year.
    Ecosystem respiration, calculated from the relation between nighttime
    exchange and soil temperature, was 7.4 metric tons of carbon per hectare
    per year, implying gross ecosystem production of 11.1 metric tons of
    carbon per hectare per year. The observed rate of accumulation of carbon
    reflects recovery from agricultural development in the 1800s. Carbon
    uptake rates were notably larger than those assumed for temperate forests
    in global carbon studies. Carbon storage in temperate forests can play an
    important role in determining future concentrations of atmospheric carbon
    dioxide.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    dioxide carbon atmospheric concentrations future determining role important play forests temperate storage Carbon studies global assumed those than larger notably were rates uptake development agricultural from recovery reflects accumulation rate observed year hectare tons metric production ecosystem gross implying temperature soil exchange nighttime between relation calculated respiration Ecosystem annual Massachusetts central forest deciduous December April continuously measure used method correlation eddy Daube Munger Goulden
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-165">
  <rdfs:label>
    Arain et al., Canadian Journal of Forest Research,
    2002.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Effects of seasonal and interannual climate
    variability on net ecosystem productivity of boreal deciduous and conifer
    forests.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Arain, M.A., Black, T.A., Barr, A.G., Jarvis,
    P.G., Massheder, J.M., Verseghy, D.L., and Nesic,
    Z.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Effects of seasonal and interannual climate
    variability on net ecosystem productivity of boreal deciduous and conifer
    forests.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2002
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Canadian Journal of Forest
      Research
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      32
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      878-891
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    The response of net ecosystem productivity (NEP)
    and evaporation in a boreal aspen (Populus tremuloides Michx.) forest and
    a black spruce (Picea mariana (Mill.) BSP) forest in Canada was compared
    using a newly developed realistic model of surface-atmosphere exchanges of
    carbon dioxide (CO2), water vapor, and energy as well as eddy covariance
    flux measurements made over a 6-year period (1994-1999). The model was
    developed by incorporating a process-based two-leaf (sunlit and shaded)
    canopy conductance and photosynthesis submodel in the Canadian Land
    Surface Scheme (CLASS). A simple submodel of autotrophic and heterotrophic
    respiration was combined with the photosynthesis model to simulate NEP.
    The model performed well in simulating half-hourly, daily, and monthly
    mean CO2 exchange and evaporation values in both deciduous and coniferous
    forests. Modeled and measured results showed a linear relationship between
    CO2 uptake and evaporation, and for each kilogram of water transpired,
    approximately 3 g of carbon (C) were photosynthesized by both ecosystems.
    The model results confirmed that the aspen forest was a weak to moderate C
    sink with considerable interannual variability in C uptake. In the growing
    season, the C uptake capacity of the aspen forest was over twice that of
    the black spruce forest. Warm springs enhanced NEP in both forests;
    however, high mid-summer temperatures appear to have significantly reduced
    NEP at the black spruce forest as a result of increased respiration. The
    model suggests that the black spruce forest is a weak C sink in cool years
    and a weak C source in warm years. These results show that the C balance
    of these two forests is sensitive to seasonal and interannual climatic
    variability and stresses the importance of continuous long-term flux
    measurement to confirm modeling results.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    results modeling confirm measurement flux term long continuous importance stresses variability climatic seasonal sensitive forests these balance that show These years warm source weak forest spruce black suggests model respiration increased result reduced significantly have appear temperatures high however both enhanced springs Warm twice over aspen capacity uptake season growing considerable with sink moderate confirmed ecosystems photosynthesized were carbon approximately transpired water kilogram each evaporation between relationship linear showed measured Modeled coniferous deciduous values exchange mean monthly daily simulating well performed simulate photosynthesis combined heterotrophic autotrophic simple Scheme Surface Land Canadian conductance canopy incorporating developed period made measurements covariance eddy energy vapor dioxide exchanges realistic newly using compared Canada mariana boreal productivity ecosystem response conifer climate Effects Jarvis Barr Black Research Forest Journal
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-166">
  <rdfs:label>
    Acker et al., Tree Physiology , 2002.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Trends in bole biomass accumulation, net promary
    production and tree mortality in Pseudotsuga menziesii forests of
    constrasting age.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Acker, S.A.; Halpern, C.B.; Harmon, M.E.;
    Dyrness, C.T.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Trends in bole biomass accumulation, net promary
    production and tree mortality in Pseudotsuga menziesii forests of
    constrasting age.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2002
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Tree Physiology
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      22
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      213-217
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:details>
    Although it is generally accepted that the rate of
    accumulation of biomass declines as forests age, little is known about the
    relative contributions to this decline of changes in net primary
    production (NPP) and tree mortality. We used 10-15 years of observations
    of permanent plots in three small watersheds in and near the H.J. Andrews
    Experimental Forest, Oregon, to examine these issues. The three watersheds
    are of similar elevation and potential productivity and support young (29
    years at last measurement), mature (similar to100 years) and old (similar
    to400 years) forest dominated by Pseudotsuga menziesii (Mirb.) Franco and
    Tsuga heterophylla (Raf.) Sarg. Accumulation of tree bole biomass was
    greatest in the young stand, reaching similar to7 Mg ha(-1) year(-1) in
    the last measurement interval, Bole biomass accumulation was relatively
    constant (similar to4-5 Mg ha(-1) year(-1)) in the mature stand, and there
    was no net accumulation of bole biomass in the old-forest stand. The NPP
    of boles increased with time in the young stand, from similar to3 to
    similar to7 Mg ha(-1) year(-1), but was nearly constant in the mature and
    old-forest stands, at similar to6 and 3-4 Mg ha(-1) year(-1),
    respectively. Mortality increased slowly in the young stand (from &lt; 0.1
    to 0.3 Mg ha(-1) year(-1)), but fluctuated between 1-2 and 2-6 Mg ha(-1)
    year(-1) in the mature and old-forest stands, respectively. Thus,
    declining biomass accumulation with stand age reflects, in approximately
    equal amounts, both decreasing NPP and increasing mortality.
  </documentation:details>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    mortality increasing decreasing both amounts equal approximately reflects stand with accumulation biomass declining Thus respectively stands mature between fluctuated from young slowly increased Mortality similar constant nearly time bole there relatively Bole interval measurement last reaching greatest tree Accumulation Franco dominated forest years support productivity potential elevation watersheds three issues these examine Oregon Forest Experimental Andrews near small plots permanent observations used production primary changes decline this contributions relative about known little forests declines rate that accepted generally Although Trends Harmon Halpern Acker Physiology Tree
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-167">
  <rdfs:label>
    Daubenmire, Botanical Gazette, 1972.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Standing Crops and Primary Prodction in Savanna
    derived from semi-decidous forest in Coasta Rica
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Daubenmire, R.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Standing Crops and Primary Prodction in Savanna
    derived from semi-decidous forest in Coasta Rica
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1972
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Botanical Gazette
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      133
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Rica forest from derived Savanna Primary Crops Standing Daubenmire Gazette Botanical and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-168">
  <rdfs:label>
    Condit et al., , 1996.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    NPP Tropical Forest: Barro Colorado,
    Panama
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Condit, R., D.M. Windsor, and S.P.
    Hubbell
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    NPP Tropical Forest: Barro Colorado,
    Panama
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1996
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Panama Colorado Barro Forest Tropical Hubbell Windsor Condit
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-169">
  <rdfs:label>
    Shaver, , 2001.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    NPP Tundra: Toolik Lake,
    Alaska
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Shaver, G.R.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    NPP Tundra: Toolik Lake, Alaska
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    2001
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:report
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Alaska Lake Tundra Shaver
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-170">
  <rdfs:label>
    Matson et al., Forest Science, 1981.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Nitrogen mineralization and nitrification
    potentials following clearcutting in the Hoosier National Forest,
    Indiana
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Matson, P.A; Vitousek,
    P.M.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Nitrogen mineralization and nitrification potentials
    following clearcutting in the Hoosier National Forest,
    Indiana
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1981
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Forest Science
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      27
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      781-791
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    Indiana Forest National Hoosier following potentials nitrification mineralization Nitrogen Matson Science and the
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-171">
  <rdfs:label>
    Smethurst et al., Canadian Journal of Forestry Res,
    1990.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Distribution of carbon and nutrients and fluxes of
    mineral nitrogen after clear-felling a Pinus radiata
    plantation
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Smethurst, P.J. and Nambiar,
    E.K.S.
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Distribution of carbon and nutrients and fluxes of
    mineral nitrogen after clear-felling a Pinus radiata
    plantation
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1990
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Canadian Journal of Forestry
      Res
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      20
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      1490-1497
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    plantation after nitrogen mineral fluxes nutrients carbon Distribution Forestry Journal Canadian and
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
<documentation:bibliographic-reference ima:id="esdbr-172">
  <rdfs:label>
    Wardle et al., Ecological Monographs, 1999.
  </rdfs:label>
  <rdfs:comment>
    Plant Removals in Perennial Grassland: Vegetation
    Dynamics, Decomposers, soil biodiversity, and ecosystem properties.
  </rdfs:comment>
  <documentation:originator>
    Wardle, David A.; Bonner, Karen I.;Barker, Gary
    M.; Yeates, Gregor W.;Nicholson,Kathryn S.; Bardgett, Richard D.;Watson,
    Richard N.; Ghani, Anwar
  </documentation:originator>
  <documentation:title>
    Plant Removals in Perennial Grassland: Vegetation
    Dynamics, Decomposers, soil biodiversity, and ecosystem properties.
  </documentation:title>
  <documentation:publication-date>
    1999
  </documentation:publication-date>
  <documentation:series-information>
    <documentation:series-name>
      Ecological
      Monographs
    </documentation:series-name>
    <documentation:series-issue>
      69
    </documentation:series-issue>
    <documentation:series-page-range>
      535-568
    </documentation:series-page-range>
  </documentation:series-information>
  <documentation:type>
    documentation:journal-article
  </documentation:type>
  <ima:keywords>
    properties ecosystem biodiversity soil Dynamics Vegetation Grassland Perennial Removals Plant Anwar Richard Watson Kathryn Nicholson Gregor Yeates Gary Barker Karen Bonner David Wardle Monographs Ecological
  </ima:keywords>
</documentation:bibliographic-reference>
</rdf:RDF>

