<!--
Copyright 2011 The ARIES Consortium (http://www.ariesonline.org)

This file is part of ARIES.

ARIES is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License,
or (at your option) any later version.

ARIES is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with ARIES.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<presentation>

  <title>Coastal flood regulation</title>
  <runninghead>Ecosystem protection of coastal lives and assets.</runninghead>
  <description>Ecosystem protection of coastal lives and assets from natural events such as
  storms and tsunamis.</description>

  <!-- The concept of the main observation (the top-level model). -->
  <concept>aries:CoastalProtectionAnalysis</concept>

  <model-storyline>coastalProtection:CoastalStormProtection</model-storyline>

  <page>
    <id>info</id>
    <name>Coastal flood regulation</name>
    <title>Model coverage and general information</title>
    <description><![CDATA[
    <p>To better idenfify the distinct economic benefits and ecological processes
    related to disturbance regulation, we separately consider the protection of
    life and property from flooding along rivers, flooding in coastal zones, and
    prevention of landslides, mudslides, or avalanches. This module
    assembles all the storylines related to for coastal flood regulation
    in the user-defined region.</p>

    <p>High-profile tropical storms such as the Indian Ocean tsunami in 2004
    and Hurricane Katrina in 2005 have spurred great
    interest in understanding the role of coastal ecosystems in
    mitigating storm surge damage. Beyond these well-publicized disasters,
    many other tropical storms and tsunamis continue to cause loss of life and
    property in coastal zones around the world. In recent decades,
    population growth and coastal migration have placed more people and
    property at risk of coastal flooding, and have also damaged or caused
    outright loss of coastal ecosystems capable of mitigating flood
    damage. In addition, climate change threatens to warm the oceans and
    melt polar ice caps. The resulting sea level rise and increased
    number and size of tropical storms can further increase coastal flood
    risk. These intersecting demographic, land use, and climate drivers
    mean that accurately valuing coastal ecosystem services and proactively
    protecting and managing these resources is important today and will
    become even more so in the future.</p>
    ]]></description>
    <see-also><![CDATA[
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/modules/coast.html" target="_blank">The coastal flood regulation section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
    </p>
    ]]></see-also>
    <credits><![CDATA[
    <b>Model development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt, Ferdinando Villa.<br/>
    <b>Funding and data support</b>: <a href="http://www.unep-wcmc.org" target="_blank">UNEP World Conservation Monitoring Centre</a>.
    ]]></credits>
  </page>

</presentation>