<presentation>
	<title>Flood regulation</title>
	<runninghead>The role of nature in protecting people and assets from floods</runninghead>
	<description>The case study</description>

	<!-- The concept of the main observation (the top-level model). -->
	<concept>aries:FloodProtectionAnalysis</concept>

	<model-storyline>floodService:???</model-storyline> <!-- Fix this, obviously: there are m\ultiple separate flow concepts for flood so it's not clear what this concept should be.-->

	<page>
		<id>info</id>
		<name>Flood regulation</name>
		<title>Model coverage and general information</title>
		<description><![CDATA[
			<p>To better idenfify the distinct economic benefits and ecological processes 
			related to disturbance regulation, we separately consider the protection of 
			life and property from flooding along rivers, flooding in coastal zones, and
			prevention of landslides, mudslides, or avalanches. This module assembles 
			all the storylines related to for flood regulationin the user-defined region.</p>

			<p>Ecological restoration focused on improving flood regulation can provide a 
			range of co-beneficial ecosystem services, which can be simulated using scenarios 
			in the ARIES flood model and other relevant ecosystem services models. For instance, 
			reconnecting rivers to floodplains through levee setbacks can provide a wide range 
			of economic benefits from ecosystem services.  ARIES provides a missing spatial 
			planning tool to explore tradeoffs between multiple ecosystem services associated 
			with forest management and other flood mitigation projects.</p>

			<p>The ARIES flood models start by mapping sources of precipitation, which can cause 
			floods, “sinks” that absorb, detain, or promote infiltration of floodwater, and the 
			location of beneficiaries at risk of flooding that may receive flood mitigation benefits.  
			Sink models incorporate vegetation and soils data that describes how well different areas 
			can promote infiltration, as well as the location of engineered flood control infrastructure 
			such as dams and detention basins.  Flood flow models spatially link sources of floodwater, 
			beneficial sinks, and beneficiaries in the landscape.  These flow models account for the 
			location and width of floodplains and the effects of levees, which both protect assets at 
			risk behind levees and speed the flow of water downstream, potentially increasing 
			downstream damage.  Different beneficiary groups may be protected from flooding – crops, 
			privately owned housing or other buildings, publicly owned infrastructure, and human life.  
			GIS data showing riverine flood zones and maps of population, agriculture, and structures 
			allows beneficiaries to be mapped.</p>

			<p>The ARIES flood regulation model currently operates using annual data for precipitation, 
			runoff, infiltration, and evapotranspiration (measured in mm/yr).  While modeling specific flood 
			events) would be desirable, the data needed to populate these models at such time scales is 
			rarely available.  The current ARIES flood models can thus be used to explore general flood 
			vulnerability, the beneficiaries of flood regulation, and the effects of flood mitigation 
			alternatives (e.g., forest management, levee setbacks) on provision of flood regulation plus 
			other co-benefit ecosystem services.</p>

		]]></description>
		<see-also><![CDATA[
		<p>
			<a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/modules/flood.html" target="_blank">The flood regulation section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
		</p>
		]]></see-also>
		<credits><![CDATA[
		<b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>
		
		<b>Additional contributors</b>: Mark Casias, Dave Batker, Jim Pittman, Paula Swedeen.<br/> 
	    
	    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">U.S. National Science Foundation</a>.
		]]></credits>
	</page>
</presentation>