<!--
Copyright 2011 The ARIES Consortium (http://www.ariesonline.org)

This file is part of ARIES.

ARIES is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License,
or (at your option) any later version.

ARIES is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with ARIES.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<presentation>

  <title>Water supply</title>
  <runninghead>Benefits related to water provision and purification.</runninghead>
  <description>The benefits of surface water supply to human users.</description>

  <!-- The concept of the main observation (the top-level model). -->
  <concept>aries:WaterProvisionAnalysis</concept>

  <!-- The storylines that this module can compute. One or more, and all their children scenarios are included. -->
  <model-storyline>waterSupplyService:FreshwaterSupply</model-storyline>

  <page>
    <id>info</id>
    <name>Water supply</name>
    <title>Model coverage and general information</title>
    <description><![CDATA[
    <p>Water supply is a critical ecosystem service, and the quantity, quality, and timing
    of freshwater in surface water bodies and groundwater are important factors in supporting
    human well-being.  While the role of ecosystems in protecting the quality, quantity, and
    timing of freshwater flows has long been recognized, payments for ecosystem services
    programs, particularly in the developing world, are rapidly emerging to protect sources
    of water supply for urban water users.  While the Millennium Ecosystem Assessment lists
    water supply and water regulation as separate ecosystem services, ARIES maps the combined
    quantity, location, and timing of freshwater flows to particular beneficiary groups
    (agriculture, industry, domestic use).  This provides a clearer view of the dependencies
    by various human beneficiaries on ecosystems for freshwater.  In ARIES, we can model
    water quality by accounting for spatial flows of sediment, nutrients, or pathogens. In
    this storyline, we describe models for quantity and timing of surface and groundwater.</p>

    <p>Given the difficulty in developing a generalized model of hydrologic processes that
    is applicable across multiple spatial scales and in different ecological contexts, the
    initial ARIES water supply models include direct data or Bayesian models (for surface
    water sinks) that are applicable to our case study regions but that incorporate the many
    of the influences on hydrologic processes that were used by other ecosystem service
    modelers.  In cases where vegetation-hydrology relationships are poorly understood,
    such as in tropical forests, ARIES’ data-driven modeling approach may be more appropriate
    than using process-based approaches.  In many other cases, future ARIES models will seek
    to link existing hydrologic models, improving model quality and credibility.</p>

    <p>Water supply is a complex ecosystem service to spatially model, given that groundwater
    and surface water are closely connected but move based on different controlling factors,
    that controls on hydrology and hydrologic models differ greatly based on the spatial and
    temporal scale of analysis and the region of the world of interest to the modeler, and
    that spatial data are unlikely to currently support modeling at both high spatial and
    temporal resolutions.  Given these limitations, ARIES' initial hydrologic models operate on
    an annual scale (which is supported by spatial data on important factors including
    precipitation, infiltration, snowmelt, and evapotranspiration).  We currently consider
    only flows of surface water, though we do model the infiltration of surface water into
    groundwater and groundwater extraction from wells. We also use a set of generalized models to
    represent sources of surface water (precipitation, snowmelt, springs, baseflow to rivers,
    and incoming inter-basin water transfers), sinks of surface water (evapotranspiration,
    infiltration), users of surface water, and the flow of surface water across the landscape.
    The long-term intent of this modeling process is to incorporate existing hydrologic models
    wherever appropriate that will more realistically account for hydrologic processes,
    including groundwater. As spatial data continue to improve, it may also be possible
    to model water supply at finer temporal scales.</p>
    ]]></description>
    <see-also><![CDATA[
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/modules/water.html" target="_blank">The water supply section of the ARIES web site</a><br/>
    </p>
    ]]></see-also>
    <credits><![CDATA[
    <b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>

    <b>Additional contributors</b>: Sharon Billings, Evan Burton,
    Linda Lucero-Dine, Octavio Perez-Maqueo, Gabriela Mendoza, Karyn
    Tabor, Allison Wagner.<br/>

    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">US National Science Foundation</a>.
    ]]></credits>
    </page>

</presentation>
