<!--
Copyright 2011 The ARIES Consortium (http://www.ariesonline.org)

This file is part of ARIES.

ARIES is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published
by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the License,
or (at your option) any later version.

ARIES is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
along with ARIES.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
-->
<presentation>

  <title>Sediment regulation</title>
  <runninghead>Benefits related to retention and removal of sediment</runninghead>
  <description>The case study</description>

  <!-- The concept of the main observation (the top-level model). -->
  <concept>aries:SedimentRetentionAnalysis</concept>

  <!-- The storylines that this module can compute. One or more, and all their children scenarios are included. -->
  <model-storyline>soilRetentionService:ReservoirSoilDeposition</model-storyline>
  <model-storyline>soilRetentionService:FarmlandSoilDeposition</model-storyline>

  <page>
    <id>info</id>
    <name>Sediment regulation</name>
    <title>Model coverage and general information</title>
    <description><![CDATA[
    <p>Erosion and sedimentation are major global problems that impose a high cost on
    the functioning of ecosystems and ecosystem service delivery. Excessive erosion and
    sedimentation have serious negative impacts on economic sectors including agriculture,
    water supply, electric power generation, and navigation. Excessive sediment delivery
    can also have negative impacts on coastal and nearshore marine ecosystems and the
    services they provide.  At the same time, natural sediment delivery can be beneficial
    process in some contexts, and the disruption of natural sediment delivery can thus have
    negative impacts.  For example, reduced sediment delivery to deltas can lead to loss
    of coastal wetlands and the critical services they provide.</p>

    <p>Spatial modeling of sedimentation has frequently used models such as the Universal
    Soil Loss Equation (USLE), Revised Universal Soil Loss Equation (RUSLE), or Spatially
    Explicit Delivery Model (SEDMOD).  USLE and RUSLE multiply five coefficients – rainfall
    runoff erosivity, soil erodibility, slope steepness and length, cover management, and
    conservation practice – to estimate soil loss over a given area and time (e.g., tons
    sediment/ha-yr).  Spatial data for soil loss and RUSLE coefficients are available, and
    using these deterministic models, where appropriate, can reduce our reliance on ad hoc
    probabilistic models.  However, USLE and RUSLE have several well-known limitations:
    1) they apply only to sheet erosion versus linear or mass erosion; 2) they have only been
    tested in regions with 1-20% slopes and are inappropriate for areas with steeper slopes
    or young mountains where greater erosion is possible; 3) energy-rainfall relationships
    have been best tested for the U.S. Great Plains, meaning that locally appropriate rainfall
    runoff erosivity coefficients must be carefully developed and applied; 4) data are not
    valid for individual storms but averages; and 5) The equations simplify interactions
    between factors to attempt to isolate the relative effects of each.  Thus USLE/RUSLE
    are likely most appropriate in level to moderately hilly landscapes with similar physical
    and ecological characteristics as the central United States; different models may be more
    appropriate in other parts of the world.  By using ARIES' internal rule base to select the
    appropriate models, we can apply the RUSLE model and data on more level landscapes and
    regionally appropriate ad hoc erosion models for steeper slopes or areas where RUSLE
    is known to be inadequate.</p>

    <p>Along with modeling and mapping sources of waterborne sediment, we model sink regions
    where sediment deposition occurs, along with users who either value beneficial sediment
    or would be harmed by either delivery of excess sediment or the presence of excessively
    turbid waterways.  Sediment regulation can thus be classified as either a provisioning or
    preventive service, depending on whether the user benefits from or is harmed by sediment
    delivery.  Running the sediment flow model allows the user to map spatial connections
    between sources of sediment, areas that promote sediment deposition, and users that benefit
    from or are harmed by sediment delivery.  In addition to these beneficiaries, vegetation
    can provide the in situ benefit of erosion control for farmers or other beneficiaries who
    want to avoid soil loss from their lands.  This benefit can be estimated by simply running
    the erosion source model in the present state and with either no vegetation or a planned
    (scenario) vegetation type, without needing to run a flow model.  The influence of vegetation
    on avoided soil erosion is thus calculated for these beneficiaries.</p>

    ]]></description>
    <see-also><![CDATA[
    <p>
    <a href="http://www.ariesonline.org/modules/soil.html"
    target="_blank">Sediment regulation model details from the ARIES website</a><br/>
    </p>
    ]]></see-also>
    <credits><![CDATA[
    <b>Model and data development</b>: Ken Bagstad, Ferdinando Villa, Gary Johnson, Brian Voigt.<br/>

    <b>Additional contributors</b>: Nathaly Agosto Filion, Brendan
    Fox, Alicia Green, Lee Gross, Dave Batker, Jim Pittman, James
    Reed, Scott Reed, Paula Swedeen, Miroslav Honzak.<br/>

    <b>Funding</b>: <a href="http://www.nsf.gov" target="_blank">U.S. National Science Foundation</a>.
    ]]></credits>
  </page>

</presentation>
